<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse vpon the present estate of France together with a copie of the kings letters patents, declaring his mind after his departure out of Paris : whereunto is added the copie of two letters written by the Duke of Guize / translated out of French and now newly reprinted, and corrected by E. Aggas.</title>
            <title>Excellent et libre discours sur l'estat present de la France. English. 1588</title>
            <author>Hurault, Michel, d. 1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120854</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150957</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150957</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28834</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 304:3 or 1880:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse vpon the present estate of France together with a copie of the kings letters patents, declaring his mind after his departure out of Paris : whereunto is added the copie of two letters written by the Duke of Guize / translated out of French and now newly reprinted, and corrected by E. Aggas.</title>
                  <title>Excellent et libre discours sur l'estat present de la France. English. 1588</title>
                  <author>Hurault, Michel, d. 1592.</author>
                  <author>Guise, Henri, duc de, 1550-1588.</author>
                  <author>Aggas, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Wolfe],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted, 1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Name of publisher from STC (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H4, I2.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  III, --  King of France, 1551-1589.</term>
               <term>Guise, Henri, --  duc de, 1550-1588.</term>
               <term>Huguenots --  France.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry III, 1574-1589.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28834:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28834:1"/>
            <p>A diſcourſe vpon the preſent eſtate of France.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Togither with a copie of the kings let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> patents, declaring his mind after his departure out of Paris.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added the copie of two letters written by the Duke of Guize.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of French into Engliſh: And now newly reprinted, and corrected by</hi> E. Aggas.</p>
            <p>Imprinted. 1588.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:28834:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:28834:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe vpon the preſent eſtate of France.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt men doo ſay, that it is a pleaſure to behold from the ſhore, the waues to ſwell, and to marke from the land howe the ſtorme and the windes play with the Sea. I beleeue it well: and it is as much to ſay, as that it is better to ſee a daunger a farre off, then to be in it. But if from the toppe of a Cliffe I ſhould perceiue a ſhippe wherein ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I had a ſhare, or my friends were encloſed, in daunger of being caſt away, and without helpe, caried againſt the rocks by the currants and tempeſt; what a griefe were it vnto me, to finde my ſelfe at ſuch a ſpectacle. If <hi>France</hi> were nothing vnto me, and I knew her ſtate as exactly as I doo, it were no matter vnto me to diſcourſe of it: when men ſhoulde bring me the newes, I would take them indifferently: yea I ſhould receiue them without any paſsion, being otherwiſe glad to be out of her broiles, and heare talke of her ſtirrings with as little commotion and feare, as if one ſhould rehearſe vnto me things that happened at <hi>Rome</hi> vnder <hi>Tiberius</hi> or <hi>Nero.</hi> I can not being a Frenchman: no I cannot ſo do, ſeeing the onely barke of my hope, the veſſel wherein I haue all that which is deareſt vnto me, and which of it ſelfe is dearer vnto me than my ſelfe, now ſee runne to wreake my countrie, my firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whom ſuch ſundrie diſeaſes haue brought to extremity, hardly panting out her laſt gaſpe. But there is no remedie: yet ſome parte of the griefe paſſeth away with crying: and ſuch wordes as ſorrow wreſteth out of our hearts, are more violent then thoſe which ioy bringeth forth. If at anie time in our affliction wee ſigh out ſome extraordinarie ſpeeches, witneſſes of our griefe, they are more liſtened vnto, then if they came from a careleſſe minde, quailed with continuall contentations: which alſo bringeth forth no other then vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar matter. Theſe accordingly ſhall deſerue commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:28834:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of their matter onely, and not for any order or methode. Others doo ſeruice vnto their countrey with their bodies &amp; goods. They doo well, ſeeing they bee able: as for me, I can but lament mine owne, I beſtow onely my teares on her, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nothing elſe left that might ſtande her in any ſteede: I commend thoſe men, let them not blame mee: I will doo as they doo when I ſhal be able: and they as I do, when they are brought to this paſſe.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Dicaeus,</hi> lying idle in the countrie whether other buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes had lead mee, I heard the firſt reporte of the kinges driuing out of <hi>Paris</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Guize.</hi> As all matters are made greater, according as men eſteeme of them, ſo was there this firſt report. Euerie one doth bring foorth his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in ſteed of comments, vpon ſuch newes as are told him. I know not whether being infected with this common vice, I did preſently gloſe vppon this reporte: well doo I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that euen then I anſwered vnto ſome that were ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to me of it, that I could ſcarſe beleeue that the matter was fallen out ſo rawly, although I did eſteeme the one capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough of ſuch a feare, yet woulde I neuer haue thought altogither ſuch preſumption to haue remained in the other. At that time or ſoone after, there were two ſundry peeces of worke brought vnto mee: the one is a declaration of the King, vpon that which happened againſt himſelfe at <hi>Paris,</hi> the 12, of <hi>May</hi>: but that ſo colde, ſo timorous as nothing more; much like vnto a man that complaineth, and yet dare not name him of whome hee hath beene beaten: like vnto a man that is afraid leaſt that his enemy bee yet in his choller, and will not be content with that harme which he hath done him alreadie. Hee dare not ſay that hee hath beene conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to flie, neither that he hath been driuen out: he dareth not terme it an iniurie, much leſſe declare, that hee will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it. Hee commandeth no more his people, but intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them. And to make vp the matter, (which is the moſt ſhamefulleſt of all) hee willeth praiers to bee made in the Churches, to the ende that this quarrell may bee appeaſed, euen as if hee ſhould feare that Monſieur <hi>de Guize</hi> were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended that he had not ſuffered himſelfe to haue been taken in the Louure, but fled away. The other cleane contrarie,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:28834:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
were two letters of the Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> the one vnto the King, the other publike, both letters of a ſouldiour, braue ones, couragious, whereby he gallantly commends himſelfe of his dooing: ſaith that God did put that daie into his hands the meanes of a notable peece of ſeruice, rehearſes it with few and ſtout wordes, without anie ſhew of feare, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinking to haue done amiſſe. Laſt of all, hee conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with a reſolute threatning, that in ſpight of all the world, he will maintaine the Catholikes ſide, and driue from the king ſuch as doo fauour the Heretikes, meaning the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon.</hi> My <hi>Dicaeus,</hi> this hath mooued mee to ſend them vnto you, you are curious of ſuch matters: and euen withall, the verie indignation hath drawen from me this diſcourſe of the ſtate of <hi>France,</hi> ſuch as it is now a daies, whereby you may iudge the better of theſe two writinges. Publiſh it if you thinke it good, ſo that you keepe in your name and mine, for wee are called to other affaires. If not, keepe it in your ſtudie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> is diuided into three factions. The Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> and his kinſmen on the one ſide: as the dukes of <hi>Maine,</hi> of <hi>Aumall,</hi> of <hi>Elbeuf,</hi> of <hi>Merceur,</hi> his brethren or couſins germaine, to my iudgement holde that which ſeemeth the greateſt, and that is it, which with their partakers, they call the holie League. The king holds the ſecond, the moſt law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but the weakeſt. The king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> and ſome Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Princes of the bloud, My Lordes of <hi>Mountmorency,</hi> chiefe Officer of the Crowne, of <hi>Turraine,</hi> of <hi>Chaſtillon,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther noble men, as well of the religion as Catholikes: the third, which may be termed the iuſteſt in deede, and as yet the ſureſt. I call the firſt, the greateſt: be it, becauſe there is likelihood that it is deriued, and as it were a member of the generall conſpiracie of all the Catholike Princes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, vnited and confederat together vnder the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Pope, to make warre againſt thoſe which make profeſſion of the religion: be it, becauſe this band is newe, and rare nouelties doo for a while carrie away all: an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof wee may gather in the ſhew that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes during the firſt troubles made in this Realme, where they had ſeiſed vppon all the good townes ſauing one or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:28834:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
two onelie, and yet within the ſpace of one yeare they had neuer a one left: or finally, for that it was framed among the Catholikes, who doo in number farre exceede the Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and who, albeit they be not wholly in all and through al of the League, do yet notwithſtanding agree in this point, that they wiſh the preſeruation of their religion, &amp; ſo ſeeme to fauour thoſe that vndertake the defence thereof: all which in deede do make this firſt faction to ſeeme the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt at this time, albeit that in troth it neither is, neither can ſo continue. I ſaide that the kinges was the lawfuleſt, No man dare denie it: So long as according to his owne will he ruled his people, he onely was obeyed, and ſo might ſtill be if he liſt: but this liſt muſt come vpon him betimes, for if it lingereth but a little longer, and that euerie man perceiue that in his dominions any man may lawfullie not onely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey him, but euen coope with him without danger, he ſhall neuer recouer his authoritie: God hath planted the meanes in his onely courage. I ſaid likewiſe that his faction was the weakeſt. It is true: albeit it ſeemeth otherwiſe, yet it is ſo, as by ſundrie reaſons we may prooue. Firſt, the king who ruleth, hath ſo behaued himſelfe that euerie man knoweth that of the three heads of the three factions, he is the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, he ſtandeth in greateſt feare, hee dareth enterpriſe leaſt: and contrariwiſe, that he is the man againſt whome euerie man dare moſt ſafely and eaſely vndertake what they liſt. He I ſay hath taken ſuch a courſe that now he hath nothing left wherewith to detaine the mindes of his ſubiects in his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſauing onely the auncient regarde that they haue of their kings, together with the cuſtome of the realme: which in truth are moſt mightie meanes in a peaceable eſtate, and yet ſuch a ciuill warre of foure yeares continuance onely, is able as eaſely to ſubuert it, as heretofore it hath don in ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpace at <hi>Rome</hi> and all other places where it hath lighted: for it ſpringeth onely of a contempt and diſdaine of the Prince, which are contrarie both to duetie and maieſtie. And then iudge you what one of thirtie yeares continuance, as ours is, may be able to doo. Secondlie, he is in his Realme the declining ſunne, and ſo weake in his declination, that euen in his preſence he ſeeth them diſpute, both by writings
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:28834:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and weapons, of him that ſhall riſe after him, In the dayes of the Romaine <hi>Caeſars,</hi> it was treaſon to ſpeake of that, that ſhould happen after the Emperours death: much leſſe durſt they name him that they thought ſhould ſucceede. <hi>Tiberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> were able to ſay ſomewhat hereof, who after a certaine ſowne that he fell into, in his olde age lying ſicke in his bed was ſtifled by his heire <hi>Caligula,</hi> a young &amp; floriſhing Prince, for feare leaſt the old man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming againe to himſelfe ſhould put him to death, only for that he was ſaluted as Emperour, when all men tooke the other to be deceaſed. So great was their power to keepe their autoritie inuiolable euen to their graues. The <hi>Ottomans</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperours will neuer ſuffer their children, whoſe poſsibilities they can not endure, to come neere them. But if we muſt needes finde a domeſticall example among our owne kings: It is ſaid, that the mightie king <hi>Francis,</hi> this mans grandfather, being weake &amp; ſicklie, was in the beginning of <hi>May</hi> in his laſt yeare, at his Caſtle of <hi>Fontainebleau,</hi> where his ſicknes on a time ſo encreaſed, that he was thought to bee dead, or not like long to liue: So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely all the Court came running to the <hi>Dolphin Henrie,</hi> who for the like gelouſie of ſucceſſion durſt not in ſixe or ſeuen yeares come neere his father: euery one ranne to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip this new ſonne, ſo as almoſt no man of account tarried about the king. Well, the king for that time recouered, and vpon the Aſcention day (a verie ſolemne feſtiuall daie in <hi>France</hi>) beeing ſomewhat eaſed of his ſickneſſe, this olde Prince ariſeth, decketh vp himſelfe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, painteth his haire &amp; his face, to hide his age &amp; ſickneſſe, appeareth himſelfe in youthfull attire, and in this arraie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth forth to proceſſion, wherein himſelfe carrieth the Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopie ouer their <hi>Corpus Domini,</hi> and at his returne vſeth theſe ſpeeches, <hi>I will ſcarre them once yet ere I die.</hi> It prooued true, the caſe was altered: for ſo ſoone as the kings recouerie was bruted abroade, all the courtiers came dropping in by one, and by one in great feare, and the <hi>Dolphin</hi> yet once againe, while his turne came, remained as ſolitarie as his father had done. This it was to be a king: yea, this it was to be feared. How manie landes be there yet in the worlde, wherein it is death to enquire who may pretend anie title to the Crowne
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:28834:5"/>
after the Princes deceaſe, ſith that is the thing that Princes doo couet to leaue moſt doubtfull. Alas! It is not ſo with our king: his weakeneſſe hath giuen all the world leaue not onely in his preſence to argue of his ſucceſſion, but alſo to ſome to endeuour to force him to prouide for it and to make his will, as if there were no more for him to doo but euen to die. His faint heart and the libertie to offende, haue brought all to that paſſe, that at this day a Frenchman may as bouldlie as a Spaniard ſay, <hi>I am not on the kings ſide:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thirtie yeare agoe, ſuch a word had beene blaſphemie, yea euen parricide. Finally, his want of courage is ſo diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that my ſelfe being in a forraine lande in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a mightie Prince confederate with the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> where there was ſome ſpeech of our eſtate, did heare one diſcourſing thereof, vſe theſe words. <hi>That our King ſtoode but as an</hi> o <hi>in Ciphre,</hi> which of it ſelfe can doo nothing, but being added to anie other number, encreaſeth the value thereof. I heard it, and with great griefe bluſhed thereat, euen for the ſhame of our Nation, albeit the diuiſions of our Realme which force vs to extraordinarie remedies had carried me thither for an other purpoſe then the particular ſeruice thereof, neither was that ſpeech any hinderance to the matter that I came about. Thirdly, he cannot aſſure him ſelfe of any of thoſe whom he thinketh to be on his ſide: for they are daunted, becauſe they ſee him quailed: They dare not fixe themſelues about him, becauſe they ſee him totter. They dare not earneſtly oppoſe them ſelues againſt thoſe that warre againſt him, becauſe they ſee him ſuffer it, and yet ſcarſe ſo bolde as to complaine. In this ſort are all his Counſaile, all his townes, and all his ſubiectes growne into factions: And I do verelie beleeue that among all thoſe that are about his perſon, hee perceiueth none, except ſome one or two that are his owne creatures, that hee dare aſſuredlie truſt: as hauing ſome other particular meaning then he, or taking part with ſome one or other of his enemies. For ſo ſoone as a king ſeemeth to feare any one within his Realme, or to miſtruſt that an other may bee greater than himſelfe, his Maieſtie is gone, he is no bodie, euery man hath recourſe to the other. Albeit we can not be free, yet will we haue but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:28834:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
one maſter: and if that maſter hath another maſter aboue him, wee ſtraight leaue the firſt to runne to the laſt: ſuch is the nature of man.</p>
            <p>As for the king of <hi>Nauarres</hi> ſide, the beginning of theſe warres do proue it to be the iuſteſt: he defendeth himſelfe, to defend it both lawfull and naturall, yea hee ſo defendeth himſelfe, as forgetting all occaſions of complaint, he alwaies made conſcience to moleſt the king (albeit in the middeſt of the wars) whom he ſee otherwiſe buſied againſt thoſe of the league, notwithſtanding he knew certainly that all thoſe iars among them would light vpon himſelfe. Neither hath hee ſo reſted, but ſo oft as he might, hee hath offered him both his perſon and goods for the recouerie of his authoritie out of the others hands, with condition afterward to ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to whatſoeuer forme of peace that his maieſtie woulde preſcribe: he hath offered it, yea euen ſince the laſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, notwithſtanding in all this warre he hath had a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand &amp; a thouſand occaſions to prooue that he is not to truſt any but God and his ſword. I haue alſo very great reaſons to tearme this as yet the ſureſt. Firſt his perſon is a great helpe: for his enimies haue done him that fauour to teach him to bee a Captaine. And ſurely ſo hee is, yea ſuch a one as may compare with the mightieſt that euer was, and albeit it hath coſt him ſomewhat, yet hath his apprentiſhippe coſt them more: his partakers are more ſtedfaſt, they regard none but him, and are retained by the dutie of conſcience, which hath vnited them togither, either for religion, or becauſe they find themſelues entred into a iuſt cauſe: hauing had a better proofe of his partakers, hee cannot feare any greater brunts then he hath already borne, neither can his enimies practiſe any nouelties againſt him: And if this thirde ſide had cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly aſſailed the other two, as they both haue done it, they had bin better ſhaken then this is. Moreouer he hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued right of naturall ſucceſsion to this realme, which no particular perſon doth any way challeng againſt him: ſo that albeit all <hi>France</hi> were agreed to take from him the crowne when it ſhould fal, yet could ther be none that ought to haue it in his ſtead: for it is a great aduantage to haue no certaine aduerſarie. Theſe vndoubted hopes do purchaſe him manie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:28834:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſeruants, and retaine him manie more, where in the meane time many mens mindes, who are loath to ſee the alteration of the auncient forme of their common wealth: being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it cannot bee compaſſed without violence, are glad to reſt vppon him, who comming in by the ordinarie gate needeth not to make any breach.</p>
            <p>This is at this day the order that is in the diſorders of the Realme of <hi>France.</hi> Theſe are the principall factions alreadie ordered and framed. Others there be that haue no ſet facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſo farre as may ſtande with the commoditie of their affaires, leaning to one of the three, they come in a croſſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeuerall purpoſes agreeing with the others, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the beginnings, though to other endes. Of theſe there are the Q. Mother, the K of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the dukes of <hi>Lorraine</hi> and <hi>Sauoy.</hi> Theſe doo very well agree in ſetting forward the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Realme, to the end to diſpoſſeſſe the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre,</hi> with the Princes of the blood, but not in the patiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. No. Each one coueteth the whole or at the leaſt the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part. Other Catholike Princes there bee of the houſe of <hi>Bourbon</hi> that remaine with the king &amp; in deed take his parte, as being vnited in religion, which is the onely ſeparation of the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> yet will neuer proceed ſo farre, as to conſent to the aduauncing of the houſe of <hi>Lorraine</hi> or <hi>Guize,</hi> before their owne: and in that caſe will rather ſupport their elder, the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> as the head of their houſe. Theſe beare great ſway in <hi>France:</hi> For were the K. of <hi>Nauarre</hi> away, the ſucceſsion of the Crowne ſhould light vppon ſome one of them: which is alſo a great hinderance to the D. of <hi>Guizes</hi> purpoſes.</p>
            <p>Beſides all theſe confuſed and yet ſeuerall diuiſions, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our miſhaps do ſeeme (as I haue ſaid) to haue already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſome ſhape and rule, euerie of theſe partakers hath his particular intent and proceedings.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> with thoſe which truely acknowledge none of the league in <hi>France</hi> but him, haue this intent and principall ſcope, to ſeiſe vpon the eſtate, either wholly or in part: a councell which by inheritance his vncle the late Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of <hi>Lorraine</hi> hath engraffed in their familie. This Prince, the ſole author of our broiles, had a father and an vncle both
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:28834:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cunning fellowes. When our diuiſions firſt beganne in the daies of the laſt king <hi>Charles</hi> betweene the Catholikes, and Proteſtants, and that they perceiued that the Prince of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> then liuing embraced the other partie, themſelues hauing bene the ſtirrers vp of the troubles, ſet themſelues on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and indeed the late Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> was already become captaine of his faction, hatching in his imagination, through his brother the Cardinals practiſes, a ſecret intent to vſurpe this crowne, either for himſelfe or his poſteritie, whereas in reſpect of the K. and his brothers minoritie, but eſpeciallie by the ciuill warres he ſee the way open. He deceaſed leauing this in maner a child vnder tuition of the Cardinall his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: from whom, euen with his Milke he ſucked the ſeedes of his domeſticall ambition, which this yoong Eagles birde did ſo well diſgeſt, that in ſhort ſpace all men might perceiue that the leaſt part in him was greater then his fathers loines. To ſay the truth, there are manie good partes bred in him, fit for great purpoſes, and for my part I alwaies tooke this mans birth to be fatall, and as it were a certaine token that God purpoſed the alteration of ſomewhat in our countrie. He onelie is the whole league: the reſt of his houſe are not equall with him: yea, they all togither are not able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the leaſt part of that which hee enterpriſeth. Full of diſsimulation, verie warie and diſcreete, and greater then al the reſt of his faction. This dooth all the world perceiue by the effectes. I haue founde it in his writings, and vnder his owne hand in a matter of great importance: where had it not beene for him, one of the greateſt of his partakers, next him ſelfe had like to haue committed a groſſe ouerfight. This is his intent and purpoſe. Now let vs ſee his proceedings, and how hee behaueth himſelfe. His miſchiefe was this, that entring into a world of affaires, there yet remained manie children in <hi>France,</hi> and thoſe in a manner of his owne age, who all were capable of ſucceſsion each after other, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and of children, which might haue beene enough to haue daunted him: howbeit all this notwithſtanding, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to feele his owne courage he was nothing aſtoniſhed: but for a time diſguiſing his drifts, he was content onelie to lay anker hold, and in the meane time to inſinuate himſelfe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:28834:7"/>
into the Catholike faction, according to the inſtructions of his familie, wherein fortune was his friend: beſides, he is of great valour, &amp; ſome of his enterpriſes haue good ſucceſſe, ſo that togither with the fame and memorie of his father, he by &amp; by framed himſelfe, through the ciuill warres which his vncle the Cardinal ſtill kindled, by one meanes or other, to bee chiefe of the Catholike faction, carrying fauour to thoſe townes eſpeciallie, which the maſſacres had continued verie ſeditious and troubleſome: and he ſtood ſtil in feare of a Proteſtant Prince, whoſe citizens hee entreated with great familiaritie, courteſie, and popular behauiors, (the chiefeſt and moſt aſſured tokens of a mind that aſpireth to tirannie). The late king <hi>Charles</hi> deceaſed without iſſue, and this king married, but hath no children: moreouer, he ſeemeth that the Crowne wanteth heires in direct line, and that the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laterals are called, whereupon he draweth neere, and already ſheweth tokens that hee craueth a part. It was giuen out in hugger mugger that he is the very ſtocke of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, thoſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alois</hi> are of the houſe of <hi>Capet,</hi> who vſurped the Crowne of <hi>France</hi> from his houſe, whereby there was ſome likelihood that he would ſcarce tarrie the death of the king now raigning, and his brother, the remnants of the children of <hi>France,</hi> before he pleaded his ſucceſsion againſt the Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terals, but would euen preuent them.</p>
            <p>Nowe was there nothing more againſt him then peace, for leaning onelie vppon the factious Catholikes, and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious townes faction: he ſhould therby loſe his credit, except the controuerſie were renewed againſt the Proteſtants. For as it is a plaine caſe, that as ciuill warre nouriſheth diuers factions in a ſtate, euen as certaine it is that a long peace o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthroweth them all, except the kings: ſo as his onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie conſiſted in ſtirring vp of coales, and returning vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ciuill weapons, and then to enterpriſe according as occaſion might ſerue. And in deede in the yeare 1578, hee made ſuch a league as this laſt, but then was the king in his full authoritie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Monſieur</hi> his brother aliue, who retained a number of french mindes, and ſo conſequently kept him ſhort of a manie: It was ſtraightwaie quenched, and wee rid of it for a little warre againſt the <hi>Huguonets,</hi> which ſoone
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:28834:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
after was appeaſed. Thus was <hi>France</hi> quiet for two or three yeares: during the which, it was incredible how many mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters his troubleſome, ambitious, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently, couragious ſtomack endured, ſuffering himſelfe to be pulled downe, and eate and dronke in diuers maners, ſo to eſchew all ſuſpition of this practiſe, which during the time of the peace, and the kings ablolute authoritie, he ſo cunninglie diſſembled, that many which knew not the laſt reaſons of this obſtinate pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, the token of a long and prophane practiſe, did euen contemne him. In the ende <hi>Monſieur</hi> the kinges brother, who was a great blocke in his waie, died. He bare him ſome diſpleaſure vppon other occaſions: for as he practiſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what about the ſtate of <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſo this man hauing priuate intelligence with the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> plaied him ſome badde partes thereabout: ſo that if he had liued (I haue heard ſome ſaie) that he would haue beene on the duke of <hi>Guizes</hi> iacke: in whoſe time at the leaſt, it had beene hard for him to haue enterpriſed anie thing in <hi>France.</hi> This death, whether it were by chance or through any practiſe, came well on his ſide: I ſaie through any practiſe, becauſe the araigments &amp; depoſitions of the lord of <hi>Salcede</hi> haue kept many in doubt of ſuch a matter. Immediatly vpon <hi>Monſieurs</hi> buriall, when there was none but the king left, hee thought that hee had gotten fit occaſion to atchieue the practiſe which his father and vncle began thirtie yeares agoe, which him ſelfe alſo with ſo great labour had nowe brought to this paſſe. Some were of opinion that about the ſame time hee had practiſed ſomewhat againſt the kings life: others that hee grounded him ſelfe only vpon ſome vaine hope and proteſtations ſent him out of all quarters, which aſſured him of the kings ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die death: But howſoeuer it was, he did not thinke it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, the ſtate ſhould be quiet at the Princes deceaſe, as knowing verie well that in <hi>France</hi> a king neuer dieth, becauſe that ſo ſoone as one is gone, there is an other ſtraightway in his place, who at his entrie would ouerthrow whatſoeuer the purpoſes that any man could commence againſt him: and therefore that it was requiſite he ſhould beare weapons againſt the heire euen before the kings death, and ſo be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the late kinges name and authoritie. According
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:28834:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
therefore vnto theſe fatherly preceptes: and with his owne domeſticall meanes he began to trouble this Realme againe in the yeare 1585. beginning firſt with the king: whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not by any perſuaſions induce to make warre vpon the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> he thought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraine by force. His pretences are, that the king hath no children, ſo as the Crowne is like to fall vnto Heretiques, whereby hee and all other the Catholikes of <hi>France</hi> are put in a fright, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeing the Proteſtant Captaines (ſo noting the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi>) are in fauour and haue their ſecrete intelligences with the chiefeſt and thoſe that are neereſt about the kings perſon. This hee ſpake of the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> who was lately returned out of <hi>Guienne</hi> where he had ſeene the king of <hi>Nauarre.</hi> Finally, verie fitlie vſing the feare that he had put the king in: corrupting all his Councell, and al that were about his perſon, hee cauſeth warre to be denounced to the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> and the Proteſtantes, which laſteth yet to this day: through the whole courſe whereof I imagine that he ſeeketh no more but ſome occaſion once to attempt, (as his fact at <hi>Paris</hi> well teſtifieth:) for as he weeneth, he needeth no more but that. Well, the warres being thus open againſt the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> euen by the kinges aduiſe, conſent, and authoritie, yet will it not ſuffice, Theſe are daylie labours. This Prince is ſtout: of great valour, he hath goods plentie, and manie friendes. There is nowe nothing to be gotten of him but ſtripes. As for his perſon it is ſafe enough, if they neither murder, nor poiſon him, as God forbid they ſhould. And for his townes, twelue Realmes of <hi>France</hi> will neuer be able to take them all. Yea, had he loſt all but his ſword, when ſoeuer God ſhould call him to this Realme, yet were that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. How many kinges haue there beene fecht both out of priſons and Monaſteries to their ſacring. In our dayes wee haue ſeene <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeuenth, who was baniſhed into the Mountaines of Auuergne, crowned. <hi>Lewes</hi> the twelfth was yet in manner priſoner in the great tower of <hi>Bourges</hi> when he was proclaimed king: neither is it credible by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie humaine apparance that the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee brought ſo lowe: and yet will not all this ſuffice. A lawfull right in ſucceſſion is a marueilous point. Theſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:28834:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
conſiderations doo breake the Dukes ambitious braine. He ſeeth that he muſt not onely make the place for the Crowne voide, but alſo he muſt make himſelfe capable both to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and vſurpe. The one conſiſteth chiefely in the king of <hi>Nauarres</hi> ſubuerſion, the other in the encreaſe of his owne wealth and credit, which will grow on but ſlenderly, ſo long as he is content with gouerning the armies vnder the kings authoritie, and of himſelfe to warre againſt the Proteſtants. A thouſand other things there are that may fall out in ſuch an enterpriſe, which would vtterly diſgrace all his affaires: and as I haue ſaide, there is not much to bee wonne from thoſe that knowe howe to defende themſelues. Againe he miſtruſted, that ſith he had perforce brought the king into this warre, he would neuer furniſh him of thinges neceſſarie for the performance thereof, but againſt his will, and yet that ſo long as himſelfe had the leading of the armies (if he compaſſed not ſuch effectes as might be woorthie the great hope and brags that he had giuen foorth) he were quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen. Theſe things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, he was content to ſend his brother into <hi>Guyenne</hi> againſt the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> while himſelfe did here ſet vpon the kings perſon: at whoſe hande he firſt hoped by ſiniſter meanes to gaine more, &amp; with leſſe loſſe. Hereupon at his brother the Duke of <hi>Maines</hi> returne out of <hi>Guienne,</hi> where he had done nothing but encreaſed the credit of the king of <hi>Nauar</hi> &amp; his lieutenant general the lord of <hi>Turraine,</hi> with whom he had chieflie had to do, they both togither with their kinſmen and partakers doe openly ſet at iarre with the king: albeit ſtill vnder their generall pretence, viz. of warring againſt the heretikes: whereupon the holines of their weapons did depende, and whereby they ſtill retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the catholike faction on their ſide. Nowe at the firſt bluſh, to ſet vpon the king it is a ſhame: they can haue no colour. There is neuer a prince of the bloud among them, neither is any of them ſo great an officer of the crowne, as that it may beſeeme him to reforme the king &amp; the realme: and yet without this, their generall pretence againſt him is to no purpoſe. The king is no catholike, he is ſuperſtitious: he hateth not the Huguonets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Huguonets are poyſon vnto him, he thinketh it a ſinne to talke with any of them,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:28834:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and that day that he hath ſo done he muſt goe to ſhrift: hee hath brought more of them to their ends then the Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> hath ſeene: he hath done them more harme than the duke of <hi>Guize</hi> wiſheth them, &amp; of him haue they more cauſe to complaine than of any of the league, the heads whereof haue alwayes ſhewed more fauor and courteſie to them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly than he, a commendation which cannot be denied them. What is the remedy then? Immediatly vpon the duke of <hi>Maines</hi> returne out of <hi>Guienne</hi> he publiſheth a libell againſt the Marſhall of <hi>Matignon</hi> the kinges lieutenant in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, whom the king had ioyned with him in office: wherin he accuſeth him of treaſon and intelligence with the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> &amp; the proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: &amp; that (ſaith he) was the cauſe that in all that iorney he could performe no great matter: yea he accuſeth him ſo couertly that he alſo taxeth the king, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he complaineth, ſaying that he cut him ſhort of coyne, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals and munition, and ſo taketh from him all meanes to atchiue anie thing: yea he proceedeth ſo far, as to ſay that he is the beſt friend that the heretikes could haue. Hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the duke of <hi>Guize</hi> on the other ſide crieth out, that it is the D. of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> who for malice toward him fauoreth his enimie the king of <hi>Nauar,</hi> and therefore reſtraineth the king &amp; maketh him to haue no care of this warre: thus for that he dareth not beat the maſter he ſtriketh the dog. That man, ſaith he, is the ſupport of al the heretiks in <hi>France,</hi> &amp; ſo he ſtirreth vp all the world againſt him: and preſumptuouſlie he proteſteth that he will not ſuffer him to haue any part, towne or gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>France.</hi> Yea albeit the kings garde be free of all ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of hereſie, yet becauſe that lord had the rule of them, he cauſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> twiſe or thriſe to be aſſaulted &amp; ouerthrowen in <hi>Picardie</hi>: and vpon this pretence doth he as well in that gouernement as elſe where ſeiſe vpon as many townes as he may. Well, the king would peruert him, and retaine his townes in obedience, &amp; to that end doth vſe ſuch power as he hath about him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are (as I ſaid) his gards &amp; thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments wherof the duke of <hi>Eſpernon</hi> is coronell. Hereupon is the quarrell proclaimed againſt the king himſelf, &amp; things brought to ſuch paſſe that the duke of <hi>Aumale</hi> beſiegeth <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loin,</hi> the duke of <hi>Guize</hi> taketh <hi>Paris,</hi> expelleth the king, ſlaieth,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:28834:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
taketh and ſtrippeth his guards, as himſelfe boaſteth. By his account euerie one that hath any townes or gouernements which he will not hold to his vſe, is an heretike: whoſoeuer endeuoureth to keep him from the kingdome is an heretike: Theſe be new articles of faith. It is ſaid that the D. of <hi>Eſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> hath ſince reſigned his gouernements into the kings hands: namely that of <hi>Normandy,</hi> which was giuen to the D. of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> I know not whether it may make him an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike alſo: which were ſomwhat ſtrange. Wel, to conclude this matter: the D. of <hi>Guizes</hi> intent is to be king if he can, his proceedings and meanes are the ciuill wars and diuiſion of the french catholikes againſt the proteſtants, whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth captaine of the firſt, with whome hee is in greater credite then the king himſelfe, or any catholike Prince of the blood. Herein let them not miſtake: for of theſe two things by his deuiſes hee hopeth for one: either ſo to ſatisfie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe during the kings life, and ſo to ſettle his affaires that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his deceaſe he may ouerthrow the king of <hi>Nauar</hi> &amp; keep him from the eſtate: or elſe, if he cannot keepe him from it, at the leaſt to force him to parley with him, who wil ſtil be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of the catholike faction, &amp; that now without example: for it hee once ouerthrow him, and with him the reſt of his houſe, this muſt needs enſue (for the one dependeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other) that either he will poſſeſſe the kingdome alone, or elſe he will deuide it with his partakers, ſtil keeping the greateſt and beſt part to himſelfe. To this banquet doth he inuite the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Pope, the Potentates of <hi>Italy,</hi> and al catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like princes near hand, to whom the mightines of the realm is as preiudicial the kings proſperity and the king of <hi>Nauars</hi> hope is as greatly to be feared, as the ouerthrow of either of them is to them profitable. But the verie worſt that I ſee in this practiſe is, that hee can in no ſort beare with the kings long life, wherof he had need to take heed: &amp; I beleeue that if hee had ſtayed but a while longer in <hi>Paris,</hi> the matter had beene diſpatched. But howſoeuer it is, I ſuppoſe that that is the thing which at this time dooth moſt trouble the one and ſcarre the other.</p>
            <p>He that ſhall now call to mind that he that is now king of <hi>France</hi> is the ſame perſon that wan the battails when he was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:28834:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but ſeuenteene or eighteene yeares old, who neuer came in place but hee had the victorie, whoſe valor and reputation euen in the ſpring of his youth purchaſed him forraine Crownes, yea crownes ouer the moſt warlike nation that wee knowe in the worlde, cannot but hee muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the onelie ſlackneſſe and miſtruſt of his owne power, which through the impreſsion of others haue ſeiſed vpon this ſometimes ſo valiant a heart, is the whip wherwith God at this day ſcourgeth our realme. Of this Prince wee muſt needs ſay, that had hee beene borne in a good worlde: had hee had ſeruants worthie himſelfe, which had loued his mightineſſe: had they not euen in his nonage cauſed him to take the affaires in hand with paine, and pleaſures with eaſe, which maketh him now to hate the one and loue the other: had no man ſince ceaſed his gouernement, and moleſted his minde, God had vndoubtedly indewed him with great good partes, whereby he might haue compaſſed great matters: but his mothers paſsions, who ſought to adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce him, to the end he might ſtand her in ſtead, with her other ſonne, thruſt him forth to labour when he ſhould haue giuen himſelfe to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: glutted him with honour before he had any ſtomacke to euill, and brought him out of taſt with ambition before he had any minde of it. Beſides al this, if a man may lawfully note any imperfection in him, this is it, that he hath beene ſomewhat giuen to loue his eaſe and reſt, which is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vice, not in Princes onely, but alſo in moſt men. In fine, comming to the crowne, he found the realme full of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe, which the long ciuil wars had brought in: and repleniſhed with factions and diſobedience: he found all his greateſt lords infected with ſeuerall purpoſes, in lieu of one generall minde that they ought to haue beene off for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: and hereto was his owne patience a great furtherance, as hauing this imperfection, that hee found no reſiſtance, if he were not croſſed, or if he liued in peace, hee would deale abſolutely &amp; with great maieſty: but if he met with neuer ſo little difficulty, he alwaies preferred a ſoft and feareful reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die before boldneſſe and ſeueritie, whereto alſo the mind of one of his chiefe counſailers of eſtate, who hath likewiſe had moſt gouernement ouer him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath beene a great helpe to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:28834:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
inure him. Hee is the firſt king that euer the captaines and gouernors of his holds compounded withall, or demanded money of to giue them vp: I meane not thoſe onely, whom the ielouſie of the ciuil wars had made partial, but the others alſo that haue alwaies take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his part. He is the firſt king whom men might boldly without feare offend. For, for my part that which another would peraduenture in a king terme clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and mercie, and which particularly he would commend in this man, becauſe he neuer ſought greatly to reuenge ſuch iniuries as many had committed againſt him, I would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; eſpecially when it doth exceed, call negligence: which is preiudiciall to his maieſtie, and which if it be not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, is not at the leaſt greatly to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended in a prince. Albeit this is to be granted, that when theſe miſerable wars began againe, God had put ſundrie good motions in his minde, and hee was entred into a way fully to reforme his realme, and relieue his people, ſo as thoſe of the league had neuer committed other treſpaſſe in <hi>France</hi> then this breaking of his good intents, yet haue they heaped a wonderfull bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of curſſes vpon their owne heads. Wel, now to returne to the preſent eſtate wherein he now ſtandeth, and his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes: vndoubtedly he hath ſuch as are moſt lawful, for they tend onely to the preſeruation of his life, &amp; maintenance of that authoritie which God hath giuen him, howbeit in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct of them he hath a very bad cauſe, cruell to his people, noiſome to his realme and dangerous to himſelfe, as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect doth ſufficiently ſhew. This mightie prince doth as well know whereat the D. of <hi>Guize</hi> ſhooteth as another: and hee hath reaſon, ſith it is at himſelfe that he chiefely aimeth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit being miſcounſailed he hath hitherto taken but a croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked way to withſtand it. Indeed he is in ſome ſort to be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as hauing no one about him, whoſe counſaile is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented either by deſire or feare, and hauing on his ſide al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt none but himſelfe. When the D. of <hi>Guize</hi> had thus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelfe vnder the name of the holy league (a name but too well knowne alredy in <hi>France</hi>) they ſtraightway propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto him a moſt falſe principle, viz. that in his realme there were but two factions, The <hi>Huguonets</hi> &amp; the <hi>Catholikes</hi>: that vnleſſe hee woulde take vppon him the gouernement of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:28834:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the one he ſhould haue none to take his part, &amp; ſo according to the prouerbe, betweene two ſtooles the taile goeth to the ground: That the <hi>Huguonets</hi> were the weakeſt and therefore that conſequently it were beſt for him to ioine with the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks, for in ſo doing he ſhould win to himſelf all the credit which the houſe of <hi>Guize</hi> had alredie gotten, which would be their deſtruction and his preſeruation: that for the atchiuing hereof he muſt ſhew himſelfe moſt paſsionate &amp; cruell to the heretikes, &amp; make war vpon them in earneſt, yea &amp; exceed al men in wiſhing their harme: and that by that onely meanes reclaiming al the catholike faction to himſelf, &amp; taking vpon him to be head thereof, he might with eaſe both ouerthrow the houſe of <hi>Guize</hi> which he both feared &amp; hated, &amp; by war rid himſelf of the <hi>Huguonets</hi> and their captaines, to whom he wiſhed no great good. This was their counſaile, which is to the great preiudice both of his realme and himſelfe, he hath hitherto beleeued: God grant he may now conſider of it, &amp; perceiue that the effects therof in lieu of making him, as hee was perſwaded, captaine of the catholike faction, haue now brought him to be the onely miniſter of the D. of <hi>Guizes</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: in ſuch ſort that ſo ſoon as the other did but ſtir againſt him, he beleeued, that to diminiſh his credite &amp; meanes, he muſt needs ſhew himſelf very buſie againſt <hi>Huguonets</hi> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon with notable commiſsions, terrible edicts, &amp; mighty ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhew himſelf rigorous to thoſe that feare &amp; honor him, and which offer him no iniury, &amp; fauorable to thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour him at his owne gate. Thus ſo ſoone as he had receiued ſome cracke by thoſe of the league, as ſoone as they began ſome mutinie againſt him, or that they ſeiſed vpon any town of his, ſo ſoone I ſay, might the king of <hi>Nauar</hi> be ſure that he would be vpon his iacke, and with all ſend an armie againſt him. Oh blinde Prince, that thought that thoſe men which willingly would haue ſeene him dead, grounded themſelues but vpon one pretence, and in caſe that ſhould faile him, hee would wreſt from them by imagination that which by force he durſt not proue! Curſſed be you that giue him counſaile. Are yee not aſhamed yee traiterous counſailers? muſt a king ſuffer factions in his eſtate? muſt he needs haue any other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne? Is it not a goodly part to be a king? If you ſay that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:28834:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
theſe two factions were there alredy, and paſt remedy: O ye wretches, who brought them in but your ſelues, that ſtill do noriſh them? Is not ciuill warre the mother of theſe factions: ceaſe that, and you ſhall ſee them flie. Let a king keepe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his ſtrength, and kinglike ſay, <hi>I will haue peace,</hi> and you ſhall ſee that the boldeſt of theſe partakers durſt not gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay it: if he muſt needs make warre, let it be againſt him that would hinder the peace, and hee will ſoone ouercome him. Neuertheleſſe, according to this principle, they made him to beleeue that there was no ſafetie for him vnleſſe himſelfe would vndertake the ſame pretence, as the fauourer of the league: alſo that it were requiſite that he ſhould in apparance ſhew himſelfe more earneſt againſt the proteſtants the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they: That the catholikes were alredie vnited with the D. of <hi>Guize</hi> againſt the others: That the onely meanes to diſunite them, was to take the D. of <hi>Guizes</hi> place, and thunder againſt the <hi>Huguonets.</hi> This was his beliefe &amp; his counſaile. In the meane time together with this perſwaſion, feare ſeiſed vpon him: yea ſuch a feare as was chiefely grounded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a iuſt miſtruſt of thoſe whom he had euen about him: ſo as ſo ſoone as he ſawe the league armed, the gates of <hi>Paris</hi> were ſcarce ſure enough for him, himſelfe viſited them, and wheras he might with his onely countenance haue ſent all the authors of this mutinie an hundred foot vnder ground, ſo ſoone as he heard of it he was amaſed: he by &amp; by ſent his mother to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them to be content: to excuſe him, for that in the time of peace he made not ſo great account of them as he ought: to promiſe that hereafter he would content them, yea that they ſhould but aske &amp; al ſhould be granted them. To be ſhort, he did in a maner humble himſelf before his ſubiects, to the end to keepe them from mutining againſt him; wheras it had bin his part to haue taught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he both would &amp; could pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their rebellion. Al this notwithſtanding he had no great mind to the war, as wiſely conſidering that it was a dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of his authoritie, and if he feared it againſt the league, hee was not deſirous of it againſt the proteſtantes: but at length being ouercome by his mother, who had other drifts in her braine then hee, and almoſt by all that were about him, he grew to a finall acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de with the Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:28834:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
perforce conſented to the war againſt the K. of <hi>Nauar,</hi> vnto whom not one moneth before he had by thirty letters of his owne hande teſtified his owne iudgement of the intents of thoſe of the league. This hath beene the counſaile that the king hath hitherto had. Now there is no doubt but he could haue wiſhed the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> to haue bene ſtrong inough to haue forced both the others &amp; himſelfe to grow to peace: but of his owne motion to propound it he neuer durſt: for had hee done it, he looked ſtraight to haue beene ſtifeled by the mutinous faction of the league. Well, hee mindeth to liue, to reigne and to be obeyed as well of the proteſtants as of thoſe of the league. A deſire both iuſt and reaſonable, and ſo he might, if he wold: but with theſe pernitious principles, ſith himſelfe calleth his power into queſtion, and dare not doo the part of a king, let him not thinke it ſtrange that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould enterpriſe to counterfeit his perſon. God grant that at length he may earneſtly deſire to be that he is, that is, the maſter and greateſt lord of his realme: but this can not be, vnleſſe he be king, and that ſhall he neuer be, except hee reſolue himſelfe to wiſh the wealth and peace of his people.</p>
            <p>As touching the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> his condition and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, it is cleane contrarie or differing from both the others, of which I haue alreadie ſpoken. Euen as he agreeth with the kings purpoſe in the behalfe of preſeruing of his life and authoritie, where againſt he neither could, neither would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing: ſo likewiſe hee differeth from him in that that concerneth the libertie of the churches of <hi>France,</hi> for the which the war is made againſt himſelfe, whiles hee goeth about to releaſe them from it. But he is euery way contrary &amp; oppoſite vnto the enterpriſes of the duke of <hi>Guize</hi> and the league. Firſt, whereas the other, to whom ambition giueth the ſame hope for the crowne of <hi>France,</hi> which right and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath giuen vnto this, cannot put it in practiſe but by warre, by the ſubuerſion of lawes, and alteration of the ſtate of the realme: for if he ſhould make no inuaſion, or if euerie thing kept their ordinary courſe, he hath no right to it, no he could not be called to it. This on the other ſide ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not looke for it but by the meanes of peace, by keeping euery thing in order, his deſire is ordinarie, and in maintaining the lawes,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:28834:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his title is lawfull. And if he would take any other way by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence or vſurping, he ſhould find his riuall as much ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſurely ſetled in this behalfe, ouer that he is, as hee hath an aduantage in the true ſucceſſion. In the meane while beſides the right of the realm which looketh on him, he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth moreouer vppon his ſhoulders the burden of all the churches of <hi>France,</hi> he beareth all their hope vpon his head: his ouerthrow to mans likelihood is their ruine and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: his greatneſſe their libertie. And that is it which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the power of his enimies, and which lincketh togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt him al the catholikes of <hi>Europe.</hi> Of truth, whiles I thinke nowe vpon this one, as I did lately vpon the other, me thinketh that God vnder theſe two mightie men, will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe our ſtate: the one hauing yet more ſtrength of bodie and minde to preſerue it, than the other hath to deſtroy it. But the other hauing as yet more meanes, by the reaſon of the opportunity which he had, to ioine with the greater ſide, and to haue had the means to vſe euen the kings authority: this will cauſe me to make ſome ſmall digreſſion to compare them together: for ſuch are they, as they well deſerue to be inſerted into <hi>Plutarkes</hi> paralels, I force my ſelfe as much as may be, to iudge of them without affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, although I ſhould in reſpect of my religion, my ſide, and infinite other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fauour the one more than the other: yet I wot not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this affection doth not robbe me of the libertie of my iudgement. But me thinketh that this man, how worthy ſo euer the other is, hath many good parts in him whereby he goeth beyond him. I ſpeake not of their practiſes, I call them not in queſtion. I do not ſo much as giue my iudgement of thoſe of the duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> but condemne them: For I am a <hi>Frenchman</hi>: I ſpeake onely of ſuch qualities as God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued them withall, proper in the one to haue them ſuch, and in the other to oppoſe himſelfe againſt them: I will ſay then that this man hath all his life through, yea from the beginning of his youth fought againſt neceſſitie it ſelfe, all his buſineſſe hath beene full of it, he neuer did any thing but with paine, the other contrariwiſe hath had all to his mind, had alwaies all opportunitie for the firſt. Item of his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, wanted alwaies rather workemanſhip than worke, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:28834:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
forme then matter, rather will then meanes. Nothing did aſsiſt this, neither did any thing reſiſt the other. This maketh mee to conclude firſt, that ſeeing by theſe ſundrie waies they haue found themſelues one as great as the other: the one muſt needs haue learned more, haue more experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce more courage, more force: the other more ambition, more hope, a thing bred in him by the greatneſſe of his meanes, &amp; by conſequent of more enterpriſe, and more audacitie. That the one hath leſſe ſhew, leſſe vanitie, leſſe pompe, &amp; leſſe bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie in his affaires: the other leſſe experience, leſſe aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and leſſe ſtabilitie. Which maketh me to thinke that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer this man ſhall find himſelfe in great abundance, hee ſhalbe better able to vſe it, then the other could defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt neceſſitie, if euer he were brought to it. I will make no mention of the former wars, wherin notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the duke of <hi>Guize</hi> had fortunes giftes alwaies at will: and this man contrariwiſe hath often tried what miſery may, yea euen the extremeſt: (I ſpeake of that whereof I wil now ſay:) that if I had ſeene this great enterpriſer aſſailed two whole yeares, by eight French armies, which were ſent to the refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing one of an other, &amp; led on a row by the beſt Captains of <hi>France,</hi> amongſt the which I account his brother the duke of <hi>Maine</hi>: and that at his departure from thence, not onely he had loſt nothing, but beſides that he had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeuen or eight good townes, &amp; wonne a great battaile, hauing in his hands no other meanes in the world to build his deedes vpon, but his courage alone, as I haue ſeene happen to the king of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uar,</hi> I would then thinke that I might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare them togither: but vntill then, there is no reaſon ſo to do. Some will ſay to me that the D. of <hi>Guize</hi> hath had many more enterpriſes and greater ones, &amp; all that the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> could do, it was to reſiſt, I grant it. It was an eaſie matter for the one to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, euerie one fauouring him: difficult to the other to reſiſt, euery one being againſt him. As the labour, ſo the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ought to be greater. They haue notwithſtanding manie humours both like and different, but no ſmall thinges, no ſlender ones. Both are of great courage, they had neede of it: both are gentle, courteous, friendly: both are actiue of bodie, vſed to toyle, and acceptable. But their mindes are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:28834:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
much diuerſe. The one is moſt honeſt, franke, openhearted, free minded, ſometimes ſomewhat haſtie, well reſolued not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding vpon preſent occaſion, and dangers: ſo earneſt about that which is ſaide before him, and ſo beſtirring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe about the vron that ought to bee beaten whiles it is hote, that he hath the leſſe regard to that which is paſſed, as alſo to that which he muſt follow: he will conceiue few farre fetched practiſes, beeing content with his hope, and refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all thereto. The other is diuerſe and as bad as may be, ſecret, cloſe, craftie, patient, euen ſo farre as to bee blamed for it, as I haue ſaide, diſſembling, laying downe his plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes a farre off. For hee muſt forge his owne hope, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a loofe off, taking nothing in hande but what hee is ſure to bring to paſſe: but I wotte not, if he were vpon the verie point of daunger, whether he would vſually growe to ſo readie a reſolution, ſith hee hath not had ſo often triall thereof. Howſoeuer the matter goeth they are both woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men, and of the woorthieſt that euer <hi>France</hi> did beare, ſuch as coulde haue performed notable actions, if a mightie king would haue vſed them, and his time haue ſuffered it. To come againe to the matter. As for the king of <hi>Nauar,</hi> he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath, neither ought to haue any practiſe about the ſtate, his poſsibilitie doth ſufficiently furniſh him, and beſides, he hath enough to do to breake thoſe of his enimies: his warre tendeth onely to peace, and the quietnes of the realme: but ſuch a peace as to the which he will neuer agree, except the churches of <hi>France,</hi> &amp; ſo conſequently the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers if he can, may be at liberty. He nedeth not plead his right to the crown it is no time: moreouer, that which is ſure, ought not to bee called into doubt or queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: much les need he buſie himſelfe about the ouerthrow of thoſe of <hi>Guize</hi> &amp; <hi>Lorraine.</hi> He wiſheth not their harm, except as they wiſh the realmes, to the which if they would bee profitable, hee acknowledgeth them moſt ſufficient, as concerning their particular perſons. Their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree is not equall with his, who vſeth the name of a king. That name keepeth him from thinking vpon theirs. His only drift &amp; purpoſe (if he hath any) tendeth to defend himſelf, &amp; after ſuch a ſort, that he may conſtrain his enimies to render vnto <hi>France</hi> hir peace, to the king his authority, to him &amp; his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:28834:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their libertie. After that, let them of <hi>Guize</hi> enrich and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance themſelues as much as they can, ſo it be not to the coſt of one of theſe three, it skils him not. The proceeding and the way that he taketh about it, is not certaine, it dependeth vpon the ſame which the others do hold againſt him. If they let him alone, he ſtirreth not: if they come to weapons, hee runnes to them: if they laie them downe, he doth the like: that is the reaſon why the king knoweth in his heart, that when the reſt of <hi>France</hi> ſhal be agreed, that there will be little or no difficultie at all with this man, who being ledde onely by reaſon, may be at all times eaſily brought to it againe.</p>
            <p>I haue ſpoken of the three principall heads which vphold the three factions that are in <hi>France</hi>: wee are nowe to marke ſuch as come in by bi-waies, what drift and ſcope they haue, whereat they aime, and what hope they haue to hit on it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe, the firſt is the Queene mother vnto the king, who for her credits ſake, and in ſhew, keepeth her ſelfe on her ſonnes ſide, as ſhe did alwaies, when ſhee had many ſonnes, hold with him that was king: but who notwithſtanding ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing more than his abſolute power, as beeing the worſe for it. When <hi>France</hi> was in peace, ſhe was faine to ſpin her rock at home, her ſon left her no charge, nor deling in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matter. That ſhe might recouer her authoritie, ſhe was fain to ſhuffell the cardes, or haue intelligence with thoſe that ſhuffeled them, otherwiſe ſhe was of no vſe: which her mind, that could not thinke on ſmall matters, could neuer brooke. And of this Princeſſe whoſe race hath ruled, &amp; ruleth at this day ouer the beſt parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> it may be ſaide as it was of <hi>Agrippa, V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ribus curis mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebria vitia exuiſſe,</hi> If that alreadie were not a vice in a woman: it hath beene alwaies her cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, in <hi>France</hi> to ſtirre vp one againſt another, that in the meane while ſhe might rule in theſe diuiſions. The mightie againſt the mightie, Princes againſt Princes, yea her owne children againſt her children. For ſhe know wel enough that our ſtate ſtandeth ſo, as that a woman, except it be by ſome extraordinarie waies, is of no credite therein.</p>
            <p>In the time of the late king <hi>Charles,</hi> this that nowe is, was then her protector, whoſe power ſhe did increaſe as much as ſhe could, to the end ſhe might vſe him to make her ſelfe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:28834:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vnto the other. The king at length perceiued it, but too late. Since that, this beeing come vnto the Crowne, wherein to ſpeake the truth, hee was infinitely bound vnto her, whiles he was in <hi>Polande,</hi> being as well aſſured that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſhee had wiſely prouided for it, there had beene ſuch ſtirringes in <hi>France</hi> as perchance at his comming home hee had beene kept from getting in. Shee kept her credite for three or foure yeares, whileſt this yoong king dreamed of nothing but the pleaſures of his age, and the deliciouſneſſe of his newe eſtate: but ſince, beginning to take vppon him the affirmatiue voice, and to ſeeke to rule alone, ſhe was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to haue recourſe vnto Mounſieur her yoonger ſonne, who for a while vphelde her, and made her to be eſteemed neceſſarie. He being deade, ſhee choſe other remedies: for howſoeuer it bee, ſhee hath euer wiſhed two thinges. The one, to make him that was in poſsibilitie of the Crowne to bee beholding vnto her, for to keepe him in when hee were come to it: The other, to make him in the meane while ſo great, that he that were maſter of the State, ſhould bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to vſe her helpe in brideling the other, employing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner verie quietly both their powers one againſt the other, that betwixt them ſhee might rule and be ſought to: ſuch a councell as particularlie for her ſelfe was as full of wiſedome as often full of troubles and inconueniences for the commons. Nowe, if after Mounſieurs death, ſhee had founde the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> fitte for theſe practiſes, ſhe had made her buckler of him: but ſeeing that his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and many other conſiderations did hinder her, ſhe hath caſt both her eyes and her heart on the houſe of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and her daughters children, whereunto the hatred that ſhee did beare vnto this Prince, euen from his infancie hath beene a great helpe: So that eſteeming her ſelfe not able to bee reconciled with him, ſhee conſequently dooth feare him, and is fully reſolued to hinder him in all that ſhee can, from getting anie part in <hi>France.</hi> Shee can neuer doo it without the ouerthrowe of the order of the Realme. For (as I ſaide) after this hatred commeth in the loue ſhee beareth vnto the children of the D. of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> who are her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters children, towards whome ſhe hath a ſecret inclination,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:28834:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
neuer ceaſing day nor night to reproch vnto the king, that he ought rather to loue as his heires, his Nephewes, his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters children, then a ſtranger vnto his houſe: ſo dooth ſhee terme the king of <hi>Nauarre.</hi> The daughters of <hi>Spaine</hi> are alſo her daughters children, vpon whome ſhe would likewiſe be glad to beſtowe ſome part of the ſame: not being grieued in the meane while that her ſons ſtate is in trouble, to the ende that he ſhould haue refuge vnto her, and that ſhe may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. Now in this manner ſhe agreeth well with the Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> to croſſe her ſonne, to ſtirre vp, and open the way to confuſion, and about the meanes to alter the order of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion in our realme: but to wiſh that hee ſhoulde waxe ſo great that he might ouerthrow the king himſelfe, &amp; diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe him, and himſelfe afterward to inuade the whole ſtate, it is not likely, I cannot beleeue that ſhe deſireth it. Now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this the Queene mothers intent, I comprehend alſo that of the Marquiſe <hi>du Port,</hi> her little ſonne, ſonne vnto the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> who likewiſe hath no intelligence or hope in this our ſtate, any further then ſhe his grandmother doth procure him to conceiue.</p>
            <p>Next, there is the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who from the beginning of theſe wars, ſeeing the Queene of England to knit a ſtraite alliance with our king, ſeeing in the ſame time alſo the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners of the low countries at <hi>Paris</hi> to offer him the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie ouer their prouinces, it came in his head to caſt three or foure thouſand crownes into the hungrie hands of the league, ſo to ſet <hi>France</hi> in troubles, as being aſſured that by theſe meanes he ſhould keepe the king from thinking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Flanders,</hi> the which he did moſt feare: as indeed, there is but the onely king of <hi>France,</hi> ſo he be in peace, that can eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take theſe Prouinces from the Spaniarde. This is that which brought him in, and conſequently, that ſomewhat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerhaſtned the Duke of <hi>Guizes</hi> deuiſes. Beſides that, hee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth now extremely, leaſt the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> ſhould attaine to the crowne of <hi>France</hi>: hee is his enimie by nature: he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth a kingdome from him, which no doubt if the others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>awes may growe on, will bee wholly pulled away, and more perchance withall. Hee knoweth well enough, that he being olde, his children yoong, his ſtate deuided and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:28834:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſcarſe ſetled, ſmall matters after his death will trouble it: much more a king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> if he were king of <hi>Fraunce.</hi> Therfore he is glad to frame himſelfe vnto thoſe of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> to finde them meanes to ſtirre vp coales, that in the meane while he may more freely goe about his warres of the lowe countries, and of Englande: to moleſt the king of <hi>France,</hi> thereby to ouerthrowe the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi>: to the end that afterward the realm being left for a pray, he being the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt, might catch the greater part. This is his drift as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our ſtate: but that he would proceede ſo farre as being burdened with many other particular expences, he wold yet draw his treaſors drie, to make the Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> king: he I ſay, who is perſwaded that if it were ſo that the maner of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion muſt needs be altered, his daughters the kinges Nie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ought to haue the better part: That which I ſay of the K. of <hi>Spaine</hi> may likewiſe be applied to the duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> his ſon in law, who is of much leſſe power, and hath no other deuiſes then his father in lawes. Theſe are all that either doo good or euill vnto <hi>France.</hi> Theſe are her good or bad humours: Theſe are the proſperous or contrary windes which torment &amp; trouble it. And of their diſcordes and paſsions as diuerſe as themſelues, as differing and contrarie as they are, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth her good or euill happe. Oh mightie Empire! the glorie of <hi>Europe:</hi> to the which the courſe of 1200. yeares could bring nothing but encreaſe, thy enemies nothing but glorie, there was ſome reaſon that after ſo manie victories, thou ſhouldeſt ende by thy owne handes, thou ſhouldeſt ſtoupe vnder thine owne force, ſeeing deſtinie had not crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the world any conquerour ouer thee.</p>
            <p>But leauing of this maner of ſpeech, which rather prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me to weepe than to write: ſeeing that the diuiſion of religion doth ſerue for a pretence in the alteration of our Realme, and ſo conſequently in his deſtruction, if God ſuffer it ſo, this euill being almoſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all the ſtates of <hi>Europe.</hi> I will ſlippe a little a ſide to ſpeake ſomewhat of the generall affaires of Chriſtendome, in that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth theſe two great factions, the one reſting yet vnder the obedience of the Pope, the other hauing caſt it off. I will not entreat hereof as a Diuine. I knowe verie well that God commonly try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:28834:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his by affections, as the meanes to keepe men in their dueties, and immediatly to haue recourſe vnto him whom they thinke but little vppon whiles their necke is ſwollen vp with proſperitie. Neither am I ignorant that the ſonne of God pronounceth theſe wordes: <hi>My kingdome is not of this worlde:</hi> thereby teaching to the true Chriſtians, that it is not here that they ought to ſeeke their eaſe, and although they finde themſelues afflicted, yet muſt they not miſtruſt of their cauſe, as if God did deteſt them, and were purpoſed to roote them out from the face of the earth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit contrariwiſe, they ſee the Turkes, the Heathen, the poore blinded ones in Popiſh ſuperſtitions, haue all at will: and conquer Realmes, furniſh Prouinces, and them of veines of golde which neuer drie vp, and their armies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper euerie where. That their good happe procureth them ſuch men as to doo them ſeruice will attempt vppon thoſe Princes liues that are their enimies, euen in the middeſt of their Gardes. Finally, they ſcarſe haue yet wiſhed, when God ſuffereth them to ſee their deſire fulfilled. Where cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe hee hath laide this neceſſitie vppon his true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes, that they ſhall take his croſſe vpon their ſhoulders if they will followe him, paſſe through the ſtraight gate, and after his example paſſe away their whole life in griefe, affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, &amp; in neceſſitie. According to theſe rules and tokens, which cannot be applyed to any other, then thoſe that make profeſsion of the true reformed religion, it might ſuffice me to conclude, that they whom God afflicteth after this ſort, are his true children, whom hee will afflict, but not vtterlie caſt away: whom he will chaſtice, but not puniſh: whom he vſeth as his children that offended him, in doing otherwiſe than he commanded them, and not as ſeruantes that haue robbed him. And after ſuch a maner, that although at this day throughout all Chriſtendome the greateſt potentates of the worlde bee confederated, vnited, and ioyned togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt them, it is all in vaine. God will neuer ſuffer that which is his to bee caſt away: they are his, hee well may dippe them two or three fingers in the water: but preſently hee will ſtretch foorth his arme of deliuerance to pull them out of the gulph: and that could I (beſides the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitable
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:28834:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
trueth of that promiſe which he made vnto his) prooue by the courſe of things that are paſſed in the church ſince the foundation of the world. But as I haue ſaid, my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is not to reaſon like a diuine. It ſufficeth me to prooue that we haue not only that great ſupernatural piller of Gods power for our defence, as an impenetrable ſhield, againſt the which, all the dartes of the worlde turne their points back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: but alſo euen in the worlde it ſelfe, and among all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine meanes he hath giuen vs without compariſon more then our enimies: ſo that if we ſuffer that they afflict vs, it is but our fault, becauſe we cannot helpe our ſelues with that power that he hath giuen vs. All Chriſtendome which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Popes obedience, is at this day ioyned togither to roote out thoſe of the religion. Who are thoſe wicked ones? let vs iudge of their power, and ſee whether it be ſo great as that we need to feare it. It is the Pope, it is the Emperour it is the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> there be certaine Potentates of <hi>Italie</hi>: In <hi>France</hi> are the duke of <hi>Guize</hi> and his kinſmen, who make the king and the realme to ſerue their turnes as they liſt. In <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland</hi> there are certaine Cantons: In <hi>Germanie,</hi> diuers prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I haue named all, and them by the moſt glorious names that I could deuiſe: there are Popes, Emperors, Kings, and numbers of Princes. It is ſaide that all theſe terrors of the worlde are gathered togither to this purpoſe onely, to make an end of thoſe which profeſſe the true religion, God grant it, ſo be it. The more enimies, the greater glorie. But let vs ſearch them a little nearer, wee ſhall finde that all theſe men haue ſome particular intent which they keepe to themſelues, and that to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>intaine their vnitie they all agree onely in the generall. What intentes? let vs ſpecially conſider of them. The Popes is manifeſt: <hi>Luther, Zuinglius,</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> haue abridged him of two partes of his reuenues: the thirde is in great danger, they labour about it. He would both recouer that which he hath loſt, if it were poſsible, and aſſure againſt hereafter, that which he holdeth. The whole realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is ſlipped out of his handes: if the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> could plant there againe the catholike religion, it were ſo much recouered for him. <hi>France</hi> hath neuer ſhewed him anie great obedience, the church of <hi>France</hi> had alwaies her priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:28834:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by her ſelfe: yet it is nothing, thinketh hee, in reſpect of that it ſhoulde bee, if euer the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> ſhould come to bee king of it. He feareth leaſt he ſhould come o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Alpes: he is of the race of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> fatall vnto <hi>Rome</hi>: beſides that hee is alreadie egged on againſt the Popes, for his kingdome of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> which moſt vniuſtly they haue paſſed ouer vnto the Kinges of <hi>Caſtile.</hi> Moreouer, he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth leaſt that a mightie Prince like vnto this, doo one day bring a great reformation in religion, which can not bee doone without diminiſhing the authoritie of the ſea: which notwithſtanding will bee as eaſie for him to doo, as it was for <hi>Philippe</hi> the faire, and manie other kinges of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> enemies to the Popes vſurpations. Thus his chiefeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is to cut this Prince ſhort of his hope. For his part hee dooth what hee can, hee thundreth, hee ſtormeth, he curſeth, hee declareth him an heretike, a rebell: finally, not capable of the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> as though it lay in him to take it away, or to giue it. For the execution of this Bull, which in deede of it ſelfe could doo but little againſt the bulwarkes of <hi>Rochell,</hi> (if that were all) he armeth all Chriſtendome, yea euen the Cardinall of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> to whome hee ſendeth a hallowed ſworde, of the race of Saint <hi>Paule:</hi> hee promiſeth money vnto the <hi>Guizians</hi>: hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, but hee ſendeth not, as hauing not yet paide that which his Popedome did coſt him, according to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh ſtile.</p>
            <p>To conclude, as it belongeth to him, hee worketh myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles with his Croſier ſtaffe, and his purpoſe and drift is, to animate all the worlde againſt the heretikes, among whom hee comprehendeth the Queene of Englande, and the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> his principall enemie to his thinking, whoſe ouerthrowe hee looketh for, by the meanes of this vniuerſall league. As much or more occaſion hath hee to complaine of the high and lowe Germanie, as of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and Englande: but hee thinketh that after that the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Guize</hi> ſhall haue chaſticed, that is to ſaie, vſurped <hi>France,</hi> and Englande, in driuing out the heretikes, that is to ſay, the true princes and lawfull lordes: after that they ſhall haue tamed the lowe countries, they may without
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:28834:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
any gaineſaying ioyne their forces with the Emperors, ſo to conſtraine either by friendſhip or force the Princes of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie</hi> which are Proteſtants, to come againe vnder the yoke of his obedience: that after that, being no great likelihood that the <hi>Suitzers</hi> woulde obſtinate themſelues againſt ſuch great forces, ſeeing their Cantons are alreadie deuided, they altogither might eaſily aſsiſt the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> to recouer <hi>Geneua,</hi> and to ſacke that towne which they call the ſpring and fountaine of all heretikes of Chriſtendome. It is there that hee concludeth the ende of his deſire, and of his holie leagues enterpriſe. Which I haue ſeene written by Pope <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> himſelfe, in a letter intercepted about the beginning of theſe troubles in <hi>France,</hi> ſent from <hi>Italie</hi> into <hi>Spaine.</hi> And as for him, this is his pretence, that is his intent grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that generall hatred which hee beareth to the heretikes, but eſpecially vnto the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and the Queene of England, of whom he hath receiued harme enough alreadie, or is afraid to receiue more.</p>
            <p>The king of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath three particular purpoſes, for the which he wiſheth this generall league. The firſt to compaſſe the warres of the lowe countries which are helde by thoſe whome hee calleth heretikes, and againſt the Queene of Englande, who is likewiſe of their number. The ſeconde his hereditarie deſire to ioyne <hi>France</hi> vnto his dominions: which hee thinketh he may nowe the more eaſily doo, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the right that belongeth vnto him through his wife, a daughter of <hi>France,</hi> and his daughters gotten betwixt them: for as for him, hee thinketh not that the Salike lawe, the honour of our kings, was made for him. The laſt, the ouerthrowe of the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> whome hee purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, whatſoeuer it coſteth him, to remooue as much as hee can poſsiblie from the crowne, for manie reaſons that hee hath to feare this great enimie, whome God keepeth for to be one day the deſtruction of his houſe. For the benefite of theſe three purpoſes, hee is come in, and hath much ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this generall league, which ſtrengtheneth to h im his ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of war againſt England: of enmity againſt the king of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uar</hi>: miniſtreth to him opportunity to enterpriſe vnder hand againſt the ſtate of <hi>France</hi> whileſt he fauoureth the affaires of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:28834:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> his partner, with whom, except it were for this, he could haue no intelligence that might yeeld him any profite: by his meanes in <hi>France</hi> he doth hope to ouerthrow the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> alſo he hopeth to vſe the hauens of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardie,</hi> and <hi>Normandie</hi> againſt England, &amp; the low countries: being ſure enough afterward, that the king of <hi>France</hi> being dead, his lawfull ſucceſſor diſpoſſeſſed, and the realme left as a pray, he ſhal be able eaſily to deuide their part vnto thoſe of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> being ſtronger then they: and thus may we ſee that he turneth the general pretence of this goodly league to his particular benefit and purpoſe, euen as though it had beene onely made for his domeſticall affaires.</p>
            <p>The Emperour would galdly, that all the other Princes of Chriſtendome which are of the religion, were ouerthrowne, to the end the whole bodie of the league might come to ſet him free from the proteſtants which are his neighbours: but becauſe it is yet a long peece of worke, and that it were not good for him to beſtirre himſelfe much, leaſt he ſhould wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thoſe mightie princes which are ſtronger then himſelfe: he ruſheth not far in amongſt them, no more then the other princes of <hi>Germanie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue diſcourſed enough of the duke of <hi>Guizes</hi> intent and purpoſe, which is to make himſelfe alone king of <hi>France,</hi> if it be poſsible, or at leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the better part: ſuch a purpoſe as willingly admitteth no fellow, &amp; for the which a man wil not lightly labour for another. This I doo heere note onely to ſhewe that to helpe himſelfe in <hi>Fraunce</hi> by the meanes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to the furtherance of his enterpriſe, &amp; in recompence thereof himſelfe to helpe the Spaniard to recouer his lowe countries: to ſee the Queene of England, to whom he wiſheth euen death it ſelfe, whom likewiſe he knoweth to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupport of his enimie, quite ouerthrowne, he wil haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table intelligence with the king of <hi>Spaine</hi>: but to yeelde him wholy the crowne of <hi>France,</hi> and to holde it of him by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, if he be able to vſurpe it, or to giue him ouer the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part, I beleeue he will not. In the meane while theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences being grounded vpon nothing elſe then the diuiſion of religion, wee muſt confeſſe him to bee one of the chiefeſt pillers of this holy league.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:28834:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>The princes of <hi>Italie</hi> haue no other purpoſe at al then their owne preſeruation, being encloſed on one ſide by the Pope, on the other by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians,</hi> on the thirde by the king of <hi>Spaine</hi>: beſides deuided, and their States ſo ſmall, that they haue ſmal leaſure to think of any other matter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues: and for this reaſon only are they come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the league. But they are not ſo good catholikes, but that they feare more the encreaſe of the houſe of <hi>Spaine,</hi> then the decay of their religion. Such as haue beene in their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries do know this</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> is alſo comprehended in this generall vnion: ſo long as his father in law ſhall liue, he will haue the ſame enterpriſes that he hath: if he dieth, he wil haue others, as I ſhall ſhewe anone, which altogither doo ſynpathiſe with thoſe of the league. The duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> likewiſe, when euery bodie ſhall come to reape the fruit of his labour, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his charges, his concluſion wil not agree with the D. of <hi>Guizes</hi> propoſition. The Cantons of <hi>Zuitzerland</hi> are not in my opinion entred into the league, becauſe of the alliance which they haue with our king, and the bonde that knitteth them togither in their countrie. Notwithſtanding I doubt not, but that for mony they will finde forces, not generallie vnto the league, but particularly to the Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> yet haue they after made ſome difficultie thereof.</p>
            <p>Of purpoſe haue I ſhewed the intent of each partaker of the league, to prooue that which I haue ſaid, that euerie one of them had ſome particular meaning diſagreeing one from another: to the end that thereby I might ſhewe, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer good intelligence they had one with another, it were verie eaſie for vs to haue a better. All with one courſe will I ſeeke out, what are their meanes and their forces: in the which I hope to finde ſo many wantes in reſpect of that which is in our handes, that we would bee aſhamed to ſuffer our ſelues to bee beaten. I will beginne with the weakeſt. Of which number I take the Emperour and the Catholike princes of <hi>Germanie</hi> to bee. For although vndoubtedly they bee of great power, yet the Proteſtantes their neighbours are of ſuch force, as euerie man dooth knowe: to witte, the king of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> the Electours <hi>Palatin,</hi> of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:28834:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Brandenbourgh,</hi> the Landgraue of <hi>Heſsia,</hi> and manie other great princes and lordes; ſo that if they woulde, the other durſt not ſeeme to haue enterpriſed any thing at all. I haue ſhewed what the forces of the Cantons of <hi>Zuitzerland</hi> are, and howe the generall league may haue vſe of them. As for the princes of <hi>Italie,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> as our neareſt neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is the moſt to be feared of them all. But firſt, it is but a ſmall matter of forces that may come from him: next, hee rather reſteth vppon ſure poſsibilities, then vppon vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine ones. His father in lawe is olde, at his death hee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to get ſomewhat, and I doo thinke that hee will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſt his cies vpon the ſtates of <hi>Millaine</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> if the ſucceſsion of <hi>Spaine</hi> come to bee deuided, as there is great likelihood: for the daughters who are as ambitious as may bee, and alreadie by their father himſelfe trained vp in the handling of affaires, and almoſt put in full poſſeſsion of his kingdomes, will hardly bee content to bee married for a peece of money, and leaue ſuch great riches vnto their yoong brother, ſicklie, and as they ſay, an Idiot: ſo that, mee thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this Duke hath worke enough cut out already, needing not to buſie himſelfe much about any enterpriſes on this ſide of the Mounts, which encloſe him in. On the other ſide beyond them, he can doo ſo little though hee woulde, and hee findeth himſelfe in a countrey ſo full of diſaduantage, that beeing of one ſide kept by the <hi>Germaines,</hi> on an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the <hi>Zuitzers,</hi> on the other by the Frenchmen, and on all ſides by the Alpes, ſuch forces as hee coulde raiſe out of his countrie, which can bee but verie ſmall, cannot bee tranſported to anie place, where they may performe anie thing without great loſſe and difficultie. As for his money, to make good cheere at home hee hath enough: but to make a great warre, not ſo. The other Princes of <hi>Italie,</hi> as the Dukes of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> of <hi>Mantoue,</hi> of <hi>Florence,</hi> and of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> which are almoſt the chiefeſt, bee all added to, for to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their rolle, and to ſay: <hi>Loe what a number here is,</hi> and not for any other matter: If there were anie warre in <hi>Italie</hi> betwixt two mightie Princes, ſuch as were <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> they might indeede much further his affaires, whome they would aſsiſt. If there muſt be an armie
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:28834:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
made vp by ſea againſt the Turke, each one of them ſhall well be able to ſet foorth a Galley or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>waine, and that is all: but that they may doo much in a great warre, either againſt vs in <hi>France,</hi> or in <hi>England,</hi> or in <hi>Germanie,</hi> or in <hi>Flanders,</hi> not ſo. Beſides that, as I haue noted, they will neuer be ſo deepe in the league, but that they will feare more the encreaſe of <hi>Spaine,</hi> then the decreaſing of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> as he is Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> may be of the number of them, but in reſpect that hee commandeth ouer the forces of the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> in the lowe countries, ſurely hee is a great captaine, without doubt he hath gotten great reputation and credite, bee it amongeſt the Armies which hee commandeth ouer, bee it amongſt the countries where he maketh warre, yea, a credite by inheritance, the remembrance of his mothers gouernment, being moſt agreeable amongſt them. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, hee were but vnwiſe, as well as the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> if he had not certaine purpoſes to himſelfe, or if hee would ſticke more to vaine poſsibilities then to certainties. For my part I beleeue, that hee is not reſolued to haue laboured all this while in <hi>Flanders</hi> for an other. But there is a farther point in this matter, which is, that as long as he ſhall make war there, as Lieutenant to the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> he may do much harme: but if once hee take the way to make himſelfe lorde of it, as he may eaſily in that which he holdeth, after the good mans death, ſeeing hee can onely perfourme it by gentle meanes, and the good will of the people, hee is not to be feared any more, but muſt needes withdraw himſelfe out of the league. As for the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> hee is a great lorde, but a pettie Prince: take away from before his eies the hope of poſsibilities, which they made him conceiue in <hi>France,</hi> for his ſonne, which only hath brought him in, with the league, hee will eftſoones take that ſide which may breede his owne quietneſſe, and not ſeeke any quarrell. Hee is verie wiſe: and therefore I beleeue that our ſtirrings in <hi>France</hi> proceede not from him at this time. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding there is no doubt but that hee employeth himſelfe in this generall matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs: but I thinke that in this point there reſteth this benefite, viz. as long as he ſhall hinder the growing vp of the Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> his coſin, as he muſt needes do, for his ſonnes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:28834:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſake, he doth vs more good, then otherwiſe he could do vs harme: now he hindreth him in reſpect of the crowne, the which at length agreeing and hauing ſome intelligence with the Queene mother vnto the king, his mother in lawe, hee will rather demand for his ſonne then for the other. And I holde it for a moſt true principle, that the duke of <hi>Guize</hi> our capitall aduerſarie, is alreadie ſo farre in, that he muſt needs either be king, or be vndone altogither: there is no meane for him betweene theſe two extremities. <hi>Marius, Cinna, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey, Lepidus,</hi> and <hi>Anthonie</hi> may be examples hereof. As ſoone as a man hath aſpired vnto tyranny, <hi>Aut Caeſar aut nihil.</hi> I haue ſpoken heretofore of his meanes: they are indeede great enough in <hi>France,</hi> becauſe the ſide of the catholikes is great, amongſt whom he is of great credit, and his aſſurance being his chiefeſt ſtrength, that the king wil put vp al his preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. But as for him, I doubt not, but that as his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular purpoſe tendeth to our ſtate, ſo, if he had in his cheſts the ducats of the <hi>Indies,</hi> he would make a breach in them, &amp; afterward doo much harme vnto others. But he is extreme poore, and indetted, the ſeconde token of a man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly aſpireth vnto nouelties. Beſides that, he hath too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that ſtand againſt his purpoſes, not only of his enimies, as the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and the princes of the bloud: but of his owne friends, as the heires of <hi>Spaine,</hi> of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> and thoſe of his owne houſe, which doo pretende as much right to the vſurping of our crowne as he doth: and to the which, ſeeing hee muſt needes vſe them for his turne as he dooth, hee muſt needes likewiſe giue ſome part of his pray, if hee can praie vpon any thing: which will breede him infinite gelouſies, ſo that all the power me thinketh, of this partner can ſtretch no farther than to the diſsipation and diſmembring of our realme: yet ſhall hee bee faine to haue helpe thereto. For, that he ſhould make warre either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Germaines, or Engliſhmen, he will hardly do it, or at leaſt it will neuer be, before hee hath made an end of his matters in <hi>France,</hi> which is a long peece of worke. And vpon that I will obſerue one moſt true qualitie of our nation: that is, that ſuch is our nature, that we can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent vnder a king that is already eſtabliſhed to deuide our ſelues, we will make
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:28834:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ciuill warres, and vproares: but if there were none, or that we were to prouide for the Crowne, wee would neuer ſuffer the renting a ſunder of it. For if a prince ſhould nor find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſet foot in the whole, he would hardly be ſuffered to diuide it, except he were a mightie Prince neere vnto it, as the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who by his ſtrength, and by the meanes of his Countries, might hold the part that hee had ketched vp: yet were it hard for him. Finally, I will vſe but two teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to ſhewe that this mans power, is no ſuch great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The one, that in the beginning of the league, when his fire was moſt kindled, when men thought that at a word of his mouth, all <hi>France</hi> would ſet vp their creſtes, hee neuer found himſelfe accompanied with a thouſand French horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and foure thouſand footmen at the moſt: yea all thoſe vaniſhed away in one moneth, notwithſtanding, that he had prodigally ſpent all the money which hee receiued out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and his owne in gathering them together. The other, that being ſince entred into the warre, a ſmall armie of rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, conſiſting of foure thouſande fiue hundred horſemen, and of three or foure thouſande Lanſquenets, with a fewe Switzers, did paſſe in ſpight of him through his gouernment euen to the verie heart of <hi>France:</hi> did beate him, and beate him againe in their paſſage, as often as they ſaw him: albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it that he had called about him all his friends, partakers, and power, and that he had beſides all this, the beſt part of the kinges: albeit likewiſe that a yeare before, he had boaſted, that he would fight with the Germaines eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Rhynes ſide, and that it ſtood him greatly vpon for his credite ſo to doo. But yet without doubt, if men ſhould ſuffer this head of a ſaction, to growe on, and except God had bridled him, he is the greateſt, the ableſt, and the moſt daungerous eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, that ſuch ſtates as make profeſsion of the religion can haue.</p>
            <p>There are yet behinde two of the worſt: to wit, the Pope, and the king of <hi>Spaine.</hi> The firſt is the brawlingeſt, the moſt ſeditious of all, and yet neuertheles the weakeſt. It is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon thing, <hi>Acutum reddere qui poſsit ferrum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ipſe ſecandi.</hi> To ſpeake the truth, he ſerueth for nothing elſe but to edge their kniues. The Popes they cannot tell an houre before
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:28834:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they are, whether they ſhalbe Pope or not. Before they come to that, they are moſt commonly pettie Italian Cardinalles (for gelouſie keepeth the greateſt from it) who during the Cardinalſhip, had no farther practiſes then to catch ſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate or benefice. Thoſe that are able to ſtirre vp coales, are not lightly preferred: <hi>Italy</hi> hath fared the worſe for it. Laſt of all, none can come by it without paying well for it: and they are all ſuch good husbandes as that they leaue as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as they can to their ſucceſſour: inſomuch that the newe Pope hath enough to doo for the three or foure firſt yeares to pay thoſe which haue ſolde him his See, and afterwarde to liue. And it is an extraordinarie thing when they paſſe nine or tenne yeares: elſe ſtraightwaies they ſay: <hi>Exiit ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo interfratres, quod diſcipulus iſte non moritur.</hi> For they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie olde when they are choſen: ſo that ere they can do any harme, they are carried to their graues. And as for this man if there were no more but he, we ſhould not neede to feare anie thing elſe then Bulles and leade, which hurt none but thoſe that are afraide of them. The king of <hi>Spaines</hi> gold were much more to bee feared: whome I haue kept for the laſt, as the greateſt of all, and the firſt moouer, who maketh all the others to mooue. But hee for his part hath likewiſe manie diſcommodities which bind his handes: and of this one, becauſe all <hi>Europe</hi> ringeth of his name, wee muſt ſay ſomewhat the more.</p>
            <p>This Prince is ſonne to <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, that great troubler of the worlde, who hath toſſed all ſo much topſie turuie, ſo long as hee was in it: who was happier by the meanes of his Lieutenantes then by himſelfe: who had eyther for his friendes or for his foes at ſundrie times all the Princes of his time: a mightie Prince notwithſtanding, vigilant, a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, (if euer there were any) and painefull in the warres: beſides full of courteſie and humanitie, and ſuch a one as truely was woorthie of the name of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and woorthie of the Empire. This ſame was brought vp in affaires by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, euen from his cradle: yet was he much more happie than he: and his good happe conſiſteth in this, that as long as his yeares could encourage him to great matters, hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mette with any that croſſed him. His father had at one
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:28834:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
time the great <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the great <hi>Henrie</hi> of <hi>England, Solyman</hi> in the Eaſt part, and the Princes of <hi>Germanie,</hi> which thoroughly exerciſed his witts: So that, on what ſide ſo euer he turned himſelfe, hee founde buſineſſe enough. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, he found all the Countries rounde about him, as ſtrong, and as like to ſet vppon him, as he vpon them. That was it, that made his fortune ſo diuerſe. Contrariwiſe, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> at this day king of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath beene fauoured with ſuch fortune as had neuer interruption. But that is more to bee attributed, to that which tell out about him, then to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>France</hi> in his time hath beene ruled by a woman, and by children, or ſo toyled by ciuill warres, that they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies founde woorke enough within themſelues. <hi>England</hi> likewiſe ruled by a woman, who following the nature of her kinde, hath wiſely contented her ſelfe with maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her ſubiectes in peace, and defending her ſtate from her neighbours attempts, not enterpriſing any thing againſt them. <hi>Germanie</hi> by peaceable Princes. The Eaſt partes by <hi>Selim</hi> a great drunkard, who tooke pleaſure in nothing but his drinke, and ſince by <hi>Amorat</hi> his ſonne, halfe an Idiot, who ſtirreth not from the <hi>Moſquetta.</hi> So that wee muſt not ſay, that he had good lucke euerie where, but that hee founde no where any bodie that might breede him any euill lucke: all which notwithſtanding, hee hath performed no great matters. The conqueſt of <hi>Portugall</hi> and of <hi>Jndia,</hi> hath beene more eaſie then luckie: there was no great labour. The conqueſt of <hi>Tercyera,</hi> and the victorie ouer the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall not ſeeme ſo ſtrange, if wee conſider that it was a whole armie of <hi>Spaine,</hi> againſt a companie of ſhips gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red togither in <hi>France.</hi> As for the battailes of <hi>Graueline,</hi> and of Saint <hi>Quintin,</hi> they were yet remnantes of his fathers victories, they were the armies that from their youth had followed the olde mans fortune, there was but little of his, his perſon it ſelfe was not there. Nothing did ſtirre in <hi>Italie,</hi> in <hi>Burgundie,</hi> in the kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> in <hi>Sicilia</hi> nothing: where contrariwiſe in <hi>Affrica</hi> hee hath loſt <hi>Goule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> the onely labour of <hi>Charles</hi> his father, and all that he had there. His victories haue not ſtretched ſo farre in <hi>Flanders,</hi> but that there is more behinde to doo. The reaſon why?
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:28834:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
becauſe hee hath founde there ſome reſiſtance. It is an eaſie matter for a man to winne, when no bodie plaieth againſt him. Nowe, euen now, hauing gotten enimies woorthie of his forces, wee ſhall ſee what he can doo in England with all his great preparations: wee ſhall ſee whether he ſhall keepe ſtill that renowmed great fortune. Concerning the ſtate that hee findeth himſelfe in at this time, it is ſuch. Firſt he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme old, and yet more broken. Hee hath but two daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and a yoong boy: they great ones, ambitious alreadie, and proud to the vttermoſt: the one Dutcheſſe of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> the other brought vp in her fathers armes, and in the affaires of his eſtate, the which ſhe alone gouerneth: his ſonne is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and ſickly, as I haue ſaide: now are theſe occaſions of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions. For in <hi>Spaine</hi> the daughters may ſucceede. Beſides that, his ſtate is much diuided. The lowe Countries, which were his beſt meſle, are farre ſcattered from him. All that which is cut off from him, as the Prouinces which are vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Queene of England, he can ſee no hope euer to recouer. That which the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> holdeth vnder his authoritie, he ſcarſe aſſureth himſelfe, that after his death he will faithfully ſurrender it vnto his children. The other is a braue Prince, a great Captaine, beloued of thoſe ouer whom he commandeth, eſteemed of the others as I haue ſaid, who hath vſed great moderation, and obſerued his faith to his people, that are alreadie highly pleaſed with that manner of gouernment, which his mother had vſed before him: who hath purchaſed great credite amongeſt them, and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to make him hereafter able to keepe this portion in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Portugall,</hi> which to his iudgement the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath taken from him: and who howſoeuer it be, will be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that all his labours ſhould be dedicated to a maid, or to a little boy. The Dutchie of <hi>Mylan</hi> is neare vnto the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi>: hee wil pretend right vnto it, in the behalfe of his wife, and according to his contract of marriage? The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the townes of <hi>Italie</hi> will follow the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of the Dutchie of <hi>Mylan. Portugall</hi> is hee as yet ſcarce aſſured of: the <hi>Portugalles</hi> greeued that <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould rule ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as much the more their enimies as they are neerer vnto them, as it is an ordinarie thing to all people. The
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:28834:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Indies</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well the <hi>Portiugalles</hi> as the Spaniſh ones, the onelie ſinnew of this ſtate, will belong vnto him that ſhall poſſeſſe either <hi>Portugall</hi> or <hi>Spaine.</hi> The caſe thus ſtanding, this Prince hath hencefoorth more neede to thinke vpon the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his houſe, and his Lordſhips (which doubtleſſe are like to be deuided after his death) then to trouble his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. To ſpeake the trueth, hee is rich: but hee is at in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite charges, ſcarſe hauing any countrie where hee is not forced to keepe a great garriſon. That he ſtandeth in neede, he maketh it knowne ſufficiently to the troupes which hee keepeth in <hi>Flanders,</hi> where he is ſometimes a yeare or eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene monethes without giuing them a pennie. As hee is rich of money, ſo hee is poore of men: hee can get none but onely out of <hi>Germanie,</hi> out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> out of <hi>Italie,</hi> or out of <hi>Burgundie.</hi> Now therefore marke his weakeneſſe. As touching the <hi>Germaines,</hi> if wee were all vnited togither, wee would keep him either from raiſing vp any, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bringing through any, the <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> of whome he can fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh no great number, (for they are no populous countries, as euerie man knoweth.) Before they can come to deale ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>France,</hi> the low countries, or <hi>Germanie,</hi> the places where wee are, he muſt leade them either by ſea, or through ſuch hard waies, that if we were all of one minde, hee ſhould looſe halfe of them before they were able to doo him anie ſeruice. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> cannot come but either by ſea, or ouer the mounts Pyrenees: The <hi>Italians</hi> ouer the Alpes, or tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough <hi>Germanie</hi>: ſuch wayes, as if wee would we might ſtop them all. Laſt of all, there is nothing more wretched than himſelfe in his owne countrie, nothing ſo eaſie to bee bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. And it is moſt ſure that hee might eaſily haue beene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne by <hi>Portugall,</hi> if he had beene liuely ſet vpon that way, ſince <hi>Don Antonio</hi> was driuen out of it. Thus haue you briefly the ſtate which the migthieſt of our enimies is in. Which to my iudgement, being well conſidered, ought not to ſeeme ſo mightie, as hee is eſteemed. The effectes with all and example doo declare it: Seeing that in twentie yeares, that he hath imployed to conquere <hi>Flanders</hi> againe, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place where he hath employed all his power, he hath not profited much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet can it not be ſaide that hee hath founde
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:28834:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
there any reſiſtance woorthie of him: notwithſtanding it is euident, that, had it not beene for the late Mounſieurs euill rule, and the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> death, moſt wretchedly by mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, a manifeſt token of this enimies weakenes, hee was almoſt driuen to diſpaire, and had loſt all theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, without anie remiſsion, whatſoeuer hee could haue doone.</p>
            <p>When our enimies ſtate ſhall thus be conſidered one by one, it ſhall bee founde according to the common ſaying, <hi>That all is not golde that gliſtereth.</hi> But if they bee yet nearer obſerued in groſſe, it will ſtande well with that iudgement which I giue of them. They ſhall be all founde farre diſtant in places and Countries. The greateſt and ſtrongeſt part is in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Italie</hi>: yet they bee diſtant foure hundreth Leagues by lande: the other is in <hi>France,</hi> but it is ſuch a ſmall thing, that if the power of <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Italie</hi> ſhoulde not ioyne together to helpe it, it woulde bee ſoone ſmothered vp. Wee ſhall ſee that each of theſe partakers, which enter into this generall League, doo bring but the leaſt part of their wiſhes vnto the generall intent, all the reſt beeing for their owne particular, wee ſhall finde that the moſt of them tende in manner to one thing: the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> or <hi>Sauoy,</hi> and of <hi>Guize,</hi> to the Crowne of <hi>France.</hi> Wherein, it cannot be choſen but that there be ſome gelouſies, and that the ſame thing which vniteth them, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth them againe. We ſhall ſee alſo, that they haue contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie purpoſes one to another, as thoſe which I haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Sauoy.</hi> And in fine, wee ſhall marke that of the two laſt, viz. the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> &amp; the <hi>Pope,</hi> who are as it were the pillers of this league: the one is extreme old and ſo ſicke, that euen this yeare hee hath giuen ouer all manner of buſineſſe: yea ſo farre foorth, that manie are of opinion that age hath bereaued him of his ſenſes. The other, which is the Pope, can make no recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his power, but ſo long as hee ſhall liue: and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering his age, hee cannot liue long, leauing perchaunce ſuch a ſucceſſour as will rather buſie himſelfe to builde vp his owne houſe, then to pull downe another mans: that wil rather deuiſe new practiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, then follow his Predeceſſors.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:28834:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Thus haue you by whole and piece <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeene all our eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies forces. Now if againſt their generall meanes we oppoſe ours generally: if wee gather together thoſe of the Queene of <hi>England</hi>: of the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi>: of the king of <hi>Denmarke</hi>: of the Princes of <hi>Germanie</hi>: of the ſtates of the lowe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and of the Cantons of <hi>Switzerlande,</hi> what a power ſhall we finde? If we vſe ours againſt them, by reaſon of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie we haue, to ioyne our ſelues without any let, <hi>France, England, Germanie,</hi> both high and low, and <hi>Switzerlande,</hi> ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one to an other, ſhall we not ſooner ouerthrow all their practiſes, than they can take them in hand? We I ſay whom our religion may knit ſurer togither then them, as beeing better than theirs: wee that haue no other purpoſe but to defend our ſelues and maintaine our rightes, which vnited vs togither: who haue no particular intent that might breed any gelouſie amongſt vs, or beeing contrarie might diuide vs. There is no doubt of it: let vs them ſee the proofe. It is three yeares agone, ſince the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> cut downe all the Foreſtes of <hi>Italy</hi> to builde his <hi>Carraqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> buyeth all the moores of <hi>Affrica,</hi> to make Galley ſlaues: turneth the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> vpſide downe, with digging and ſeeking to finde out an the Goldmines, as though he had no more to do hereafter. It is three yeares agone ſince he had no other ſpeech but of Ankers, of Cables, of ropes and ſayles: ſince hee threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Ocean, if it doth not vſe his ſhippes gently: ſince that hee chargeth the windes to fauour them, and all this to make vp a mightie and ſpaniſh (that is to ſay) proud ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie by ſea, whoſe ſhadowe alone may cauſe not onely the maſts of ſhips, but alſo all the toppes of the ſteeples of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to ſtoope. For theſe three yeres ſpace he is with child of an armie. And to ſpeake the truth, as theſe great peeces of worke are not ſoone brought foorth, nor with eaſe, ſo he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth much time &amp; labour to be deliuered of it: but things commonly are leſſer at their birth then men thinke of. Then in the end it ſhall be borne in <hi>Biſcay,</hi> weaned at Conquet, and finding it ſelfe right againſt Englande, it ſhall haue ſtrength and ſtature enough to receiue the order of knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. Doth not this proue, that in one only place, viz. Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande we are able to reſiſt the moſt dangers of our enimies?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:28834:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
It is three yeares ſince hee threatned it, hee hath not yet ſo much as made it afraid. Tuſh, when will he be able to hurt it? It is as long ſince the Duke of <hi>Guize</hi> (who in a maner plaieth with the king and the realme of <hi>France,</hi> his power being hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen with money out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> with the forces of the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> and all the Catholike ſtates) maketh warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi>: in which ſpace there hath beene eight armies by land leuied to that purpoſe, and the ninth by ſeas. Of nine of them thankes be to God, eight are gone backe againe without doing any thing: the ninth hath been quite ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a battaile. Now, if it can not be ſaid that this poore Prince was in the meane while aſsiſted eyther with one pennie or one man, the money &amp; helpes which his friends had ſent him, being not yet come as far as vnto him, is it not a certaine proofe that this people hath more facing than doings. It is twenty yeares ſince that the low countries are ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſame king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> with all the forces that he could make out of his countrie, out of <hi>Italy,</hi> and all thoſe that he could get out of <hi>Germany.</hi> He hath bin alwaies fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in it. Almoſt all the battailes that haue bin fought there he hath wonne. What hath he done. They are yet at this day in ſuch a caſe, as if they can once haue good correſpondence one with an other, he is to begin of new, &amp; in danger of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his labor, his paines, &amp; his charges that he hath laid out in that country. Iudge you now, if ſo it were that the king of <hi>Denmark</hi> the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> &amp; the Cantons of the <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers,</hi> which they durſt not meddle withall, had brought their helpes &amp; forces to make theſe violent dealings of the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>England</hi> to ceaſe, and thoſe of <hi>Guize</hi> in <hi>France</hi>: how long to mans iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, were they able to ſtand before vs? I leaue more to conclude hereupon, that I ſpeake not of. In the mean while, although we haue mo forces then they, that we haue better meanes of intelligence one with an other, yet doo they agree better one with an other then we do, &amp; are ſtronger than we are. Let vs returne that reproch vnto our negligence: and not attribute it vnto their indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie: to our baſe minds, and not to their courage. God hath put into our handes the meanes both to liue at reſt &amp; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their tyranny: yea &amp; to bring them vnder
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:28834:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the yoke, if wee would ſo doo. But to make an end of this ſpeech diuine like, euen as I haue begun it, I beleeue that it is the ſame God, and the ſame Lorde, who will not haue vs to hold our deliuerance as from our ſelues, neither from our owne arme, but from him alone.</p>
            <p>Mee thinketh that my minde is nowe much eaſed, when that after I haue runne ouer all <hi>Europe,</hi> which is altogether almoſt troubled and afflicted with diſſentions in religion, I returne vnto <hi>France,</hi> which I thought onely to haue beene plagued with this euill. God viſiteth not it onely, neither is it alone threatned: other places haue their part, I returne then to her againe better ſatiſfied then I was, to conclude this diſcourſe which I began for her ſake. This viſarde, this vaile, which had bleared vp firſt the kings eies, and after him all the Frenchmens, is at length pulled away. When the league began firſt, three yeares agone, there were men yet that were either ſo without ſhame, or without ſenſe, as that they excuſed this rebelling, they ſhadowed it with a zeale of religion, with a care, leaſt that after a good catholike king, there ſhould ſucceede him a Huguonet. This ſerued the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors pretence that were about the Prince, whom they knew ſo dedicated and paſsionate towards his owne religion, that euen with this worde they ſtopped his mouth, they tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him all manner of replying together with all the meanes that he might vſe to iudge what he had to do about this matter. But nowe, I do not thinke that there is any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in all the realme, nay not the verieſt <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> that could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Duke of <hi>Guizes</hi> attempt at <hi>Paris,</hi> againſt his owne king. What a maner of one it was, I deſire no other diſcourſe then his owne, the very ſame which he hath publiſhed. Now if one ſhould aske what, in my minde will enſue vpon it? hee ſhould trouble me ſhrewdly. I haue ſaide elſewhere, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more dangerous for a king, then the empairing of his Maieſtie: that there is nothing which diminiſheth it more, then if hee ſhewe, that hee feareth ſome bodie in his realme: it is a kinde of feare, to ſuffer preſumpteouſnes, and not puniſh it: Yet when it is but a common preſumption which concerneth particular ones, the cloke of gentle cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie ſometimes doth excuſe thnorouſneſſe: but if it bee
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:28834:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
towards the Prince himſelf, if it doth violate the holy reſpect which men owe to the ſacred perſon of the king: whoſoeuer ſuffreth them, is no longer king. If this vnexcuſable treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie be pardoned, if the king letteth it ſlippe vnder ſilence, it may be well ſaid, <hi>Sceleris finem putas? gradus eſt.</hi> And there is no doubt but that within theſe two yeares there will be ſuch bold and villanous actions committed, as that this ſhall bee counted but for a light tricke of youth. I am of the reformed religion, thankes be to God, who hath vouchſafed to make me ſuch an one: me, I ſay, who through the forgetfulneſſe of his great benefites, had made my ſelfe altogether vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of this latter one, which is not to be compared with any other: neuertheleſſe, if ſo it were that the king ſhould thinke that the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> and wee with him had attempted ſuch treacherous and deteſtable practiſes againſt his life, and eſtate, that with good conſcience hee might not pardon vs. God forbid, that vnder pretence of this quarrell I ſhoulde counſell him to call vs to him, to forget our offences, and to vſe our helpe to bring him out of thoſe troubles, whereinto hee is put daylie by his owne folkes. But not as a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, not as a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but as a man, I dare wel counſel him. What, counſaile him? nay prophecie, that if this argument of the wrath of God againſt him, doth not ſtirre him vp to wiſh his owne good, and with his owne good, the quietneſſe of this realme: the way of peace: the meanes to become a king: to take away all part takings out of his realme, except his owne: and as the Scepter belongeth to none but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, not to ſuffer it to bee broken in peeces, and euerie one moſt vnwoorthilie to carrie away a morſell of it, himſelfe being the firſt, and moſt true cauſe of his miſchiefe, let him bee aſſured, that in ſteede of taking it away from him, God will encreaſe it double folde vnto him. I will not only ſpeake of thoſe of the league. I doo yet ſpeake of our ſelues. That which others do through wickednes, we do it by neceſſitie: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding al is a like to him in regard of his crown: it is as well ſpoyled, and pulled a ſunder by the one as by the other: his people as much troden downe by vs as by the league. And were it not that we defend our ſelues, wher they ſet vppon vs: that where wee are purſued, they purſue: that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:28834:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
where wee ſubmit alwaies our ſelues vnto him, the others would ſubmit him vnto them: it might be well ſaid, that the harme which we doo perforce vnto his realme, is as great as that which they doo for their pleaſure, and to ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ie their ambition. For this euill, alas, there is but one remedie: let him onely take vpon him to remedie it, hee may be a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and abſolute king, obeyed, feared, beloued, dreadfull, if he liſt. But what do we wiſh that God ſhould put the power into his handes, except firſt hee hath the will in his heart? Mightie Prince, why dooſt thou not beleeue thy ſelfe? thou haſt nor ſo faithfull a counſailour. I haue hearde thee heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore blame the king of <hi>Portugals</hi> fault, who aduentured all his ſtate vppon one battaile: as iudging wiſely, that there is nothing more miſerable then a diſherited Prince. Oh! where haſt thou laide vp thy wiſedome? thou ventureſt thy ſelfe vppon leſſe a hundreth times then a battaile. Who hath bin able to perſwade thee, that theſe men who haue no other deſire then thy death, no other ſcope then thy crowne, will lay downe their weapons which they haue vowed againſt thee onely, when they ſee thee bitterly bent, and verie cruel againſt thoſe of the religion? No no, thou muſt giue ouer thy crowne, elſe thou ſhalt neuer haue peace with them: and I beleeue if thou couldeſt giue it ouer without danger of thy life withall, thou haſt enough about thee that haue ſuch bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen faces, as to counſell thee thereto. They haue driuen thee out of <hi>Paris</hi> which neuer the Engliſhmen, the Spaniards, nor the Germaines did thy great grandfathers: yet by thy let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patents thou ſheweſt vnto thy people, that in ſtead of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging thy ſelfe of it, it ſeeme th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thou thinkeſt it verie long, vntil they haue pardoned thee. Thou comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pray to God for this reconcilement: there is then belike no other da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to lift vp any mans hand againſt his king. Beleeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he that durſt to day make thee flie, wil dare to kil thee to morrow. But is not this, oh mightie king, an aduenturing of thy ſelfe, when thou letteſt thy ſubiects perceiue that it is ſo eaſie a matter to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt againſt thee: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſtead of reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging thy ſelfe, thou praieſt that thoſe may be pacified, whom thou oughteſt to haue puniſhed? Who could ſo miſchieuouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thee that the remedy of my miſchief was the ciuil war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:28834:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that by that courſe thou ſhouldeſt recouer thine authoritie ouer thy ſubiects. Alas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how art thou deceiued? There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more dangerous in a building then fire: in a bodie, then a continuall feuer: and in a ſtate, then a ciuill warre. If thou wilt remedie theſe euils, quench the fire which burneth thy houſe: aſſwage the continuall feuer of the bodie of thy eſtate, giue it peace. For that is the onely meane to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thy realme. Thou ſaiſt that if thou ſhouldeſt but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce this worde of peace to them of the religion, thou ſhouldeſt haue preſently vppon it all the catholike armies of Chriſtendome againſt thee, which wil ſpoile thee of thy ſtate. Yea if thou pronounceſt it as hee that latelie fled away from <hi>Paris,</hi> before the duke of <hi>Guize.</hi> But pronounce it as he that wanne the battailes of <hi>Iarnac</hi> and <hi>Moncontour,</hi> who alone wert more dreadfull then all the reſt of thine armie: vtter it onely after that ſort, that thou ſhalt finde all men to tremble.</p>
            <p>If vpon this good and holie reſolution, thou wilt arme thy ſelfe, <hi>England, Germanie,</hi> &amp; <hi>Suitzerland</hi> will couer all thy plaines with horſe and armed men, for thy ſeruice. They will ſend thee ſufficient forces to beate <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Italie,</hi> yea and thy <hi>France,</hi> if it were ioyned with them. Thinke thou that this will be firſt the benefit of thy realme, and it will be eaſie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſo to perſwade thy people, when thy ſelfe ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue it. And thy people, if thou bee willing of it, they will account all ſuch as ſhall wiſh the contrarie to bee their enimies and thine. But thou feareſt the league: Who then ſhall bee bolde for thee: whence ſhall wee take courage but from thine. Grant a reaſonable peace and quietneſſe vnto thy ſubiectes, begin with thine owne firſt: with the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, make them to bee content with reaſon, and feare not then but the reſt wil be brought to it: they are too weake to ſtand againſt thee in an euill cauſe. Such a one will theirs be if they refuſe an indifferent peace: but they will not doo ſo: they neuer did it. It is too common a prouerbe in thy court. <hi>Let them be pleaſed with a ſermon.</hi> Thou art yet afraide: good Lord of whom? of the king of <hi>Spaine</hi>? Shew him the pictures of thy father, and thy grandfather, and he will tremble euen to the fartheſt of <hi>Caſtile.</hi> Of the Pope? Haſt thou not yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee ſome heires of <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi>? theſe are but
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:28834:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
toies. How can it bee poſsible, that thou who haſt ſeene ſo much, who haſt handled ſo many matters, who haſt ſo great experience, canſt haue this apprehenſion engraued ſo deepe within thee, and vppon ſo ſmall an occaſion? Beleeue theſe two principles: the one, that thy enimies haue their beſt friende of thee: the other, that if it were not for that blacke cloud which thou ſeeſt about <hi>Rochell,</hi> which they feare more than thee, they would haue buried thee long agone: but yet adde this third alſo, and beleeue it, that whenſoeuer thou ſhalt earneſtly wiſh the good and reſt of thine eſtate, it ſhall lie in thy power to be maſter, to bring as well the one as the other ſo farre vnder, in reſpect of thy obedience, and thy place, that they ſhall not be able to turne an Egge, without thy leaue. They perſwade thee, that the ſtrongeſt ſide is the catholikes, and that thou muſt needs ground thy ſelfe verie deepe therein, and become chiefe of it, to take away this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle from the Duke of <hi>Guize.</hi> They perſwade thee, but they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thee. The parties ought not to receiue thee, neither thou to go vnto them. They ought to come to thee, &amp; thou to receiue them. To be a king is thy part: thou haſt no need of any other: let all the reſt yeeld vnto this. What meaneth this? that a king of <hi>France</hi> ſhoulde enter into gelouſie with a Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> that he ſhould be put in danger of looſing his credit by his meanes. Doeſt thou not know that this gelou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie maketh thee equal? and preſently being equal, inferiour? well may there be ſteps to clime vp to a crowne, but there is none to come downe: it is a downe right fal. If a king come neuer ſo little downeward, he falleth down right. They coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell thee to feigne thy ſelfe ſore angred againſt vs: after thou haſt feigned a while, thou becommeſt ſo in earneſt. They yet deceiue thee more, and were it not for thy affection to thy religion, thou mighteſt iudge eaſily of it. Aſſure thy ſelfe that this D. which becommeth ſo mightie in thy realme, keepeth to no otherend the beſt part of that which he hath with him, but onely becauſe it is to thy ſelfe that he hath a meaning to. Dooſt thou thinke that thoſe which ſerue him haue no other ſcope then the deſtruction of the <hi>Huguonets</hi>? No, no. What is there to be gotten againſt them? If I had giuen my ſelfe ouer to follow him, for my part I would thinke to haue done it, in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:28834:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
reſpect of his hope to be king one day. For that he ſhould be thought well of in reſpect of his zeale towards his catholike religion, in putting manie Huguonets to death, it will ſerue to raiſe vp all the porters of <hi>Paris,</hi> and make them crie: <hi>Haue amongſt the Huguonets.</hi> Thoſe which are ſufficient to helpe him to turne vp a realme, haue other conſiderations then that. Now theſe conſiderations are not put out of their heads, by thy fierce countenance againſt thoſe of their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thy quaking lookes towards the league. This is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, the way to encreaſe them, their helpes, their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and their authoritie. When men ſee, that thou ſheweſt, that thou art thy ſelfe afraide of them: who then ſhall not feare them? What emboldeneth men, but impunitie? Of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wee loue to be at libertie. There was neuer any realme but that it did ſtriue to become, if it were poſsible, a popular eſtate. There is nothing that a prince ought to keepe more preciouſly then his reſpect, his maieſtie, and his feare: which being once loſt, can neuer bee recouered, but onely by ſuch things as breed feare, that is to ſay, by violence and crueltie. Mightie king, thou ſhalt accept this ſpeech as it ſhall pleaſe thee: it belongeth not to mee to limit thy purpoſes. But if thou readeſt it with as much paſsion for thine owne good, as I write it, thou ſhalt thinke, if any too violent a word dooth eſcape me, yea againſt thee, that it is the verie indignation and hart burning that forceth mee vnto it, when I ſee the wrong and iniuries that are done vnto thee: to the which it ſeemeth after a manner, thou dooſt conſent by thy patience. Do not thinke that I did meane to accuſe the courage which is in thy ſelfe: all <hi>Europe</hi> woulde giue me the lie: and if thou wouldeſt haue any witneſſes of it, thou ſhouldeſt neede none but our ſelues (whome thou haſt beaten ſo often) to ſpeake of it. Verelie beleeue, that the griefe which I conceiue to ſee thee ſuffer through euill counſaile, thoſe bolde partes which are onelie attempted vppon confidence that thou wilt ſuffer them, doo wreſt this both out of my heart and my penne. I knowe that all thoſe which are about thee, haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to betraied thee: that that which thou haſt done againſt thy ſelfe, thou haſt done it by taking that counſell, where by contrariwiſe other princes do moſt commonly erre, that is,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:28834:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by beleeuing of counſaile. I was preſent when it was tolde thee, that all thy townes, all thy people, all thy prouinces were alreadie the duke of <hi>Guizes,</hi> all thy men were his. They told thee it, but none other then themſelues that tolde thee it, were belonging vnto him: and tkey did tell thee it to no other end, but onely to ſell thee, and betray thee vnto him. The ſtrongeſt armies of the league which are againſt thee, haue beene in thy court, in thy counſell, in thy priuie cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. So that it was verie hard but that thou ſhouldeſt be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by ſo many thinges contrarie to thy good purpoſes. But ſeeing that God in this laſt danger where into hee had brought thee, hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away al excuſe, &amp; occaſion of doubt, let this at the leaſt giue thee a mind to loue thine owne ſelfe more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt done: to will earneſtly thy own good, thy reſt, thy highneſſe: and when thou ſhalt wiſh it, thou ſhalt by conſequent, wiſh thy realmes withall.</p>
            <p>I wil end in thee, thou firebrand of the war, which haſt tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the deſtruction of thy king and countrie, thoſe great graces which God had giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, for to haue bin able to haue done worthie ſeruice as well to the one, as the other. Dooſt thou not thinke to bee puniſhed one day for the parricide which thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteſt againſt thine own mother, for ſo many euils that thou art cauſe of, or which thou doſt thy ſelf to her, who hath done thee ſo much good? ſo many euils I ſay, the which thou mighteſt haue remedied, either by deſiring leſſe, or by deſiring more wiſely, or at leaſt, by bringing in thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires at length into ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe? Nay, nay: thou needeſt no other puniſhment the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine own practiſes. They are thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Poore ſoule, thou art almoſt forty yeres old, &amp; yet da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou not take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee the name of a king: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wilt thou bring it to paſſe? Thinkeſt thou to make eaſily an end of thoſe which can barre thee from thy vaine hope? For theſe thirtie yeares, men haue loſt their labor in making war againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I wil abate thee ten vpon the bargaine, thou haſt yet twentie left. What a king art thou like to be at thoſe yeres end, being 60. yeares old? Thou haſt bin heard ſcoffing at the cardinall of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> whom thou hadſt perſwaded to haue been one at that age: ſcarce wilt thou come ſooner to it, &amp; yet muſt many things come well to paſſe for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee. Thou wilt ouerthrow the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:28834:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> (a vaine labour, I am ſure both for thee and thy children) dreame rather to ſaue thy ſelfe from him: his clawes are greater than thine: but I grant it, thou ſhalt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw him: and it were ſo, how wilt thou do to raigne? If after his ouerthrow <hi>France</hi> lyeth open to the ſpoyle, as it can hardly chooſe: art thou ſtronger then the king of <hi>Spaine</hi>? haſt thou more right than he hath? More than the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> who is ſonne vnto a daughter of <hi>France,</hi> and nearer of bloud than thou, &amp; is married alſo vnto a daughters daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>France</hi>? More than the Duke of <hi>Lorraines</hi> ſonne thine elder, the ſonne likewiſe of a daughter of <hi>France,</hi> and the kings Nephew. If contrariwiſe the eſtate be kept whole and found, howe wilt thou lawfullie take away the right from the Catholike Princes of the bloud which ſhalbe remaining, who are yet in number enough, and young enough to liue as long as thou, except thou ſhortneſt their liues? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, before all this commeth to paſſe, who can perſwade thee, that the king who reigneth now, will not keepe thee from reigning? thou canſt not ſo long as hee ſhall liue: thy firſt blowes muſt beginne with him (that canſt thou do well enough) thou muſt make him awaie: for he hindreth thee tenne thouſand times more than the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi>: and except this bee thy firſt intent, thou haſt no iudgement in thy practiſes. For thou canſt not poſsibly, whileſt he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, bee a king, neither continue long ſo, in taking the courſe that thou dooeſt: but thou purpoſeſt to reigne. What then poore wretch, except this bee it that driueth thee on? except ſome great and mightie ambition dooth puffe vp thy minde, ſuch a one as ſometimes poſſeſſed either <hi>Marius, Sylla,</hi> or <hi>Caeſar,</hi> thou ſhouldeſt be accurſed enough heereafter, for hauing wrought ſo much miſchiefe in the worlde to no ende. Ambition is the plague of humaine ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie: notwithſtanding, it hath alwayes moſt gloriouſlie ſet foorth by manie and woorthie deedes all ſuch as haue beene poſſeſſed with all. Let vs blame ambitious men, yet doo wee admire them. If thou canſt beare ſo woorthie a minde, as to looke for a kingdome, there will bee found heereafter ſome bodie that will ſaie, that thou wert woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to haue beene borne a king, ſith thou couldeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:28834:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to haue beene one. Such miſchieues and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as thou muſt needes breede, to bring it to paſſe, ſhall not be paraduenture imputed vnto thee: but it ſhall be ſaid, that fortune would by theſe meanes make thy comming notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that thou wert too great to come foorth by an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie gate, and that thou muſt needes haue ruines to receiue the and make thee roome. <hi>Nec aliam venturo fata Ner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenere viam.</hi> Thou ſhalt alſo be found fault withall: but many that ſhall finde fault with thee will wiſh to be like vnto thee: otherwiſe thou wretch, if vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a villainous mind thou haſt no other end of the euill which thou doeſt, then to hinder the benefite and quietneſſe of all the world; what will our poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſay of thee? who amongeſt them will not call thee the ſcourge of our age? But ſeeing thou canſt not be king, thou haſt no minde to be it: it is enough for thee to trouble and diuide our eſtate, to the end thou maiſt keepe the better part for thy ſelfe. Thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe yet more wretched. Had not God endued thee with ſufficient vertue for to deſerue an honorable portion at their handes, to whom all by right doth belong, who would haue beene alwaies ſo glad to haue thee about them as their kinſman, as thou art: and in ſteede of a good and profitable ſeruant as thou mighteſt haue bin? Hadſt thou not rather haue beene beholding to thy Prince for thy good, in beſtowing thy ſeruice vppon thy countrie, then to a forraine Prince in ouerthrowing it quite? Marke what thou doeſt: thy father, and thy grandfather haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted vnto the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> his part in <hi>Italy:</hi> and thou wouldeſt allot him it in <hi>France: Sic ne patriſſas?</hi> Yet is not this all? What then? The onely zeale vnto the catholike religion doth kindle thy heart? Thou ſaieſt it (I beleeue) in the face of the world, not in thy Cloſet: nay I am afraid, except thou vſeſt ſhortly other maner of termes, leaſt thou repenteſt to haue driuen thy king out of <hi>Paris.</hi> He is not an heretike, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but he is a king. Whoſoeuer ſhall be it, either in deede, or poſsibilitie, he is thine enimie. Thou wilt make it knowen at length, that it is onely for that that thou medleſt with the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and that thou art more gelous ouer his poſsibilitie then his conſcience: I beleeue it well. And if ſo be it were that he would ſuffer thee to be king, thou wouldſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:28834:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
eaſily grant him to be a Hugnonet. It is thy zeale vnto reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: good Lorde! What, to encreaſe it? There are yet ſo manie Turkes and Sarraſins aliue which keepe from thee thy kingdome of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> belonging by inheritance to thy houſe: why doeſt thou not rather bende thy practiſes that way, then vpon the realme of <hi>France?</hi> To defende it? Tuſh, who dealeth with it? who durſt ſay any thing againſt the Catholikes? My opinion then is, that thou ſhouldeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs that the wolues ought to take heede leaſt the ſheepe might ſurpriſe them, that Lions were beſt to miſtruſt the Deere. Thou ſaieſt the verye ſame. Where there is one of the religion in <hi>France,</hi> there are a hundred Catholikes. If the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> ſhould take that courſe, as to perſecute them during the kings life, he ſhould be euill handled: if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſhould be worſe receiued. Nay, alledge not theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes: men laugh at them. Say onely that thou wouldeſt reigne, thou wouldeſt be king: it is the trueſt and the beſt colour of thy Enſigne.</p>
            <p>I will conclude at length, and in two or three wordes aunſwere thoſe Letters which thou haſt ſpred abroad. Thou publiſheſt firſt that thou wert the onelie man that diddeſt ſet forwarde the voyage of <hi>Guyenne, (Id eſt,</hi> againſt the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi>) to the which thou haſt ſuch a minde. But what needeſt thou to ſtirre vp an other? Why goeſt not thou thy ſelfe? Seeke out there either a victorie or an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable death, as the Duke of <hi>Ioy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe</hi> did. Make offer vnto the king to go in thine owne perſon. Hee will take thee at thy woorde: carrie thither all thy friendes, all thy forces, he will encreaſe them with his owne. Carrie thither the fire of war, ſeeing it is there that thou ſhouldeſt finde thine enimies, and thou ſhalt finde them in deede. Why doeſt thou kindle it in <hi>Pycardis</hi>? is there any heretikes alſo there? I would to God that <hi>Caliis</hi> and <hi>Bulloine</hi> were as well minded towardes the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> as thou chargeſt them to be: thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt bee kept well enough from quarrelling at <hi>Paris.</hi> Thou ſhouldeſt haue leaſure enough to encloſe thy ſelfe within <hi>Challons,</hi> and thinke vpon nothing elſe but thine owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. This is the matter. Thou wouldeſt that the king ſhould leaue in thy handes the protection of <hi>France,</hi> and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:28834:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that hee ſhould goe and make warre in thy quarrell in <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enne,</hi> that hee ſhoulde ouerthrowe thine enimie the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> that hee ſhoulde giue order vnto thy affaires, to the ende, that whileſt hee ſhoulde there buſie himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the beating of ſome ſconce, thou mighteſt heere take ſome good towne from him: and vppon condition, that whenſoeuer hee would returne, he ſhould giue thee roome, as often as it ſhoulde pleaſe thee. I grant thee it: it is well and wiſely conſidered of thee: but yet is hee wiſer than thou art, in that hee will not doo ſo. Thou ſaieſt that the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon</hi> fauoureth the Heretikes: all thoſe that barre thee from beeing king are Heretikes, according vnto thy rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning: or at leaſt, they fauour them. There will be then enough in the worlde, if God will. Thinke this to bee moſt ſure, that if that man woulde haue had but the leaſt intelligence of the worlde with the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> if hee had put into his hands euen the leaſt of thoſe townes which hee had in his power, or holpen him neuer ſo little with that commoditie of money that hee might haue hadde, there had not beene roome enough in <hi>France</hi> to haue hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thee: thou ſhouldeſt haue beene vndoone alreadie, I ſaie quite vndoone. Giue him thankes for thy preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which his fidelitie hath purchaſed thee, to his owne coſt and his maſters. He is come, ſaieſt thou, to ſeeke quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relles in <hi>Pycardi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and in <hi>Normandie.</hi> What part haſt thou in theſe two Prouinces? Of the one, my late lorde the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was gouernour: in his abſence, there were Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants from the king: of the other, the Duke of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> was the like. Neither thou, nor any of thy kindred haue anie right vnto it.</p>
            <p>But ſoft, I muſt needes excuſe thee: thou wouldeſt reigne: all is lawfull for thee. Thou dooeſt complaine moreouer, that there haue beene ſlanders ſpredde abroade againſt thee, and thine honour, the which (thankes bee to God) thou haſt blotted out by this latter facte of thine. Thou art a maruellous Oratour: ſurely it is true, thou haſt well cleared thy ſelfe. Thou wert accuſed to haue ſtirred vp the people of certaine townes of this Realme, againſt ſuch gouernours as the king would haue appointed. Thou
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:28834:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
haſt taken this ſlander away, in raiſing vp them of <hi>Paris</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king himſelfe. Thou wert blamed to haue ſeiſed vpon his money at <hi>Challons,</hi> at <hi>Rheymes,</hi> at <hi>Soyſſons,</hi> and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where that thou ſetſt thy foote. Thou haſt purged thy ſelf in taking that of his owne ſtore in his chiefe towne. Thou wert ſuſpected to haue certaine enterpriſes againſt the ſtate, and to aſpire vnto the crowne, &amp; that to that purpoſe thou hadſt alreadie ſeiſed on ſome good townes, which either thou or thy parents did hold, to the which the king woulde not haue obeyed. Thou haſt put away this falſe report by thy perſonall comming to make thy ſelfe maſter of <hi>Paris,</hi> and driuing out of the king, after thou hadſt forced, killed, and vnarmed his guard, and cauſed the common people to riſe in armes againſt him. So that after this ſort thou gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wipeſt away a theft with a ſacrilege: a murder with a parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide: a ſinne with a crime. Thy ſubtletie is too groſſe. Thou triumpheſt, that thou durſt come with eight Gentlemen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Paris,</hi> a token of thy pure innocency. Theſe be great news. Be thou in <hi>Rochell</hi> with all thy new court, all thy traine, and all thy guard: the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> will come in with foure men, and if going away thou doeſt not flie, hee will trouble thee. This is eaſie to be ſaid in <hi>Britaine</hi>: but thoſe that know that all the kinges councell ſtand for thee, that his mother fauoureth thee, that all the pickquarrels, all the porters of <hi>Paris,</hi> and all the common people are at thy becke: they will ſay that thy ſimplicitie was verie craftie, thy innocencie much ſuſpected. How wilt thou haue vs to beleeue that thou haſt truſted ſo gently vnto the king, ſeeing that after the League was made, when you made your worthie agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at S. <hi>Mor,</hi> thou wouldeſt neuer come to him before that thou wert as ſtrong as hee, ſeeing that whileſt hee hath beene in his armie againſt the Reyters, thou neuer haſt ſet thy foote towards him, ſauing once when thou diddeſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe him, and that but a quarter of an houre. Nay, beleeue mee: it is thy occupation to worke ſuch feares, but not to excuſe them: thou canſt better doo the one then the other. It is plaine enough, ſeeing thou vaunteſt thy ſelfe, that thou mighteſt haue retained thy king, againſt his will. Ah, what ſaieſt thou, thou ſtranger? retaine a king of <hi>France</hi>? It is all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:28834:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that <hi>Europe</hi> being confederated were able to doo: it is the enterpriſe of an Emperour, yet a verie dangerous one. If thy Grandfather had thought, that thou wouldeſt euer haue pronounced theſe words, he would haue ſmothered vp thy father, to let thee from comming into the world: in a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able eſtate, in a quiet realme, that worde onely would haue coſt thee thy head. That is likewiſe the reaſon why thou trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt it.</p>
            <p>As for the reſt of thy publike letter, all the wordes of it are too plaine, too well ſet downe to be found fault withall. Whileſt thou makeſt a diſcourſe of thy valour, they ſhewe what is thine intent better than any man can do. I will onely note the end of it, where thou ſaieſt, that thou haſt ſeiſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Baſtille,</hi> the <hi>Arſenall,</hi> and other publike places, the kinges Coffers and Exchequor, to ſurrender all againe into his Maieſties handes well pacified, as thou hopeſt to bring to paſſe by the Popes interceſsion, and other the Princes of Chriſtendome: if not, with the ſame helpes thou wilt trie to reskue the Catholikes out from the perſecution of thoſe that are about him, and fauour the heretikes. What a braue dilemma is this. I beleeue, thou meaneſt not by pacified, peaceable or appeaſed, but in ſuch ſtate as that he be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make warre againſt thee: which thou hopeſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure by the forces and helpes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Italie</hi>: that is the interceſsion which thou meaneſt. And in fine, thou meane and ſimple ſubiect denounceſt war againſt thy king. Others endure it, thou beginneſt it. If the late Emperor had but ſaid ſo much to his father, all Chriſtendome woulde haue beene vp in armes, both of one ſide, and other, vpon this worde. If God alſo ſtirre vp his heart, I hope it will be thy laſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A declaration of the Kinges pleaſure, publiſhed after his departure from Paris: importing the cauſe of his <hi>ſudden and forced going away.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRuſtie and welbeloued. Beeing in our towne of <hi>Paris,</hi> where we bent our onelie cogitations to no other thing but the appeaſing of all ſortes of ielouſies and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:28834:31"/>
in <hi>Pycardie</hi> &amp; elſe where, which hindered our iourney into our countrie of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ictou,</hi> there to proſecute the wars en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſed againſt the <hi>Huguonets,</hi> according as we had reſolued; our coſen the Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> vnwares to vs, did there arriue the 9. of this moneth. His comming after that ſort ſo encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſaide gelouſies &amp; diſtruſtes, that we were much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled therwith: the rather for that before we had from diuers places beene aduertiſed, that he ſhould come in ſuch maner: alſo, that he was looked for, by ſundry the inhabitants of the ſame towne, who were ſuſpected to be the authors of the ſaid diſtruſtes, beſides that our ſelfe had before for the ſame cauſe giuen him to vnderſtand, that wee were nothing deſirous of his comming before we had appeaſed the aforeſaid troubles of <hi>Picardy,</hi> &amp; quite take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away the cauſes of the ſame. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring neuertheleſſe, that he came accompanied only with 14. or 15. horſes, we were content to ſee him, and that the rather to the end to endeuour ſo to deale with him, that all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of gelouſie and diſtruſt might be extinguiſhed: wherein ſeeing howe ſmallie wee profited, as alſo that our ſaid towne grewe daily more and more repleniſhed with gentlemen and ſtrangers, retainers to the ſaid Dukes traine: alſo that ſuch ſearches, as we cauſed the magiſtrates and officers thereof to make, were through the feare wherinto they were driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to halfes: likewiſe, that the hearts and affections of ſundry the inhabitants were daily prouoked, and more and more alienated: togither with the ordinarie aduertiſements whereby we were from time to time enformed of ſome great troubles to fall out in the ſame towne, wee determined to cauſe the ſaide ſearches to bee more exactly performed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout al the quarters therof than the former: to the end therby to diſcouer &amp; truly find out the ſtate of the ſame: alſo to auoid ſuch ſtrangers as ſhold be found not to be aduowed as they ought. For the performance whereof we thought it good to ſtrengthen certaine the bodies of the gardes of the inhabitants &amp; burgeſes of the ſame towne whom we had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be planted in 4. or 5. corners thereof, with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of <hi>Zuitzers,</hi> and ſuch as were of the regiments of our guard: who before were lodged in the ſuburbs: alſo to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand diuers the lords of the councel &amp; knights of our order
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:28834:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the holy ghoſt, to march along the ſtreetes and quarters therof acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with the quarter maſters &amp; others the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the ſaide towne, ſuch as haue beene vſually accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to make the ſaide ſearches, to the end by their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to authorize &amp; aſsiſt them in the ſame, as hath ſundrie times bin practiſed. Whereof alſo we gaue notice to the ſaid Duke, &amp; all the inhabitants of the ſaid towne, leaſt any ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhould take allarome, or any whit doubt of our intent in this point: which order at the beginning the Burgeſes and dwellers ſeemed to take quietly and in good part: howbeit within a while after matters grewe ſo hot, &amp; that the rather through the induction of diuers who wandring vp &amp; down enformed the ſaid inhabitants that we had not brought in the ſaid forces for any other end, but only to eſtabliſh forrein gartiſons within the towne aforeſaid, yea, and to deale worſe then ſo: wherby in ſhort ſpace they had ſo animated &amp; ſtirred them vp, that if we had not expreſſely forbidden the leaders of our troopes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attempting any thing againſt the ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, &amp; withall commanded them rather to beare and indure all extremities then to offer any violence, we doo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly beleeue that it had bin vnpoſsible to eſchew the generall ſacke of the towne, &amp; much bloudſhed. This when we perceiued, we determined to ceaſe the execution of the ſearches aforeſaid, alſo to cauſe our forces to retire, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we had not brought in, but vpon that only occaſion: as alſo it was no other like, but that if we had me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t otherwiſe we wold haue atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, yea, &amp; peraduenture put in execution what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer our purpoſes, before the riſing of the ſaid inhabitants either that they had drawen their chaines or erected their defences in the ſtreetes, which immediatly after noone they went in hand withal, and in a maner in one inſtant through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the ſtreetes of <hi>Paris,</hi> being thereto induced and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by ſundry gentlemen, Captaines, &amp; other ſtrangers ſent in by the ſaid duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> who to the ſame end, in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſhort ſpace appeared, diuided and aranged throughout euerie quarter of the towne. Hereupon cauſing the ſaid <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> and french companies, to returne, the ſaid inhabitants to our great griefe diſcharged diuerſe Harquebuze ſhotte, and dealt ſome blowes which light chiefelie vpon the ſayde
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:28834:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Switzers,</hi> whom the ſame euening we commanded to retire &amp; lodge about our Caſtle of the <hi>Louure,</hi> there to expect the euent of this commotion of the ſaid towneſmen: for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing wherof, we did al that poſsibly we could, yea ſo farre forth, as the next day to procure all the ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies, except ſuch as before their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in, we had placed in gard before our ſaid caſtle, to depart the town, as being enformed that in ſo doing, we might greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent &amp; pacifie the ſaid inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants: as alſo we cauſed to ſtay ſome remainder of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of foot men of the regiment of <hi>Picardy,</hi> albeit they were 7. or 8. leagues off, togither with diuers lords and gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſeruants that drew vnto vs: as conſidering that the ſame had bred ſome ſhadowe to this people, alſo that they tooke hold of this pretence, whereby the more to prouoke and ſtir the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp. Al this notwithſtanding, in lieu of finding our wiſhed effect to their owne benefit &amp; our contentation, they neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ſtill proceeded in raiſing their bulwarkes, ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their gard night &amp; day, &amp; approching the ſame toward our ſaid Caſtle of the <hi>Louure,</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the very ſentinels of our ordinarie guard, as alſo they ſeiſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the townhouſe of the ſame towne, togither with the keyes of <hi>S. Amthonies</hi> gate &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the gates therof: ſo that by the 13. of this moneth, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were run ſo far, that it ſeemed vnpoſſible by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s power to ſtop the effect of greater violence &amp; commotion, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our ſaid caſtle gates. This when we perceiued, and being neuertheles vnwilling to employ our ſaid forces againſt the ſaid inhabitants, as hauing euermore held the preſeruation of the ſaid towne with the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts therof, as deere as our owne life, as in ſundry their occaſions they haue wel tried, &amp; is euident to al men, we determined the ſame day to depart, and rather to abſent our ſelues, &amp; abandon the place which aboue all the world we moſt loued, and ſo doo ſtill deſire to doo, then to ſee it incurre further hazard, or receiue greater domage: hauing withal entreated our moſt honorable Lady &amp; mother to ſtay, &amp; try whether ſhe might through her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; autoritie in our abſence be able to find any means, howe to appeaſe the ſaide tumult, which notwithſtanding, whatſoeuer her endeuors, ſhe could not in our preſence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and ſo are come into this our towne of <hi>Chartres,</hi> from
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:28834:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
whence we thought good immediatly to ſend you theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, therein deſiring you to conſider of the conſequence of this cauſe, how preiudiciall and hurtfull it wil be, in caſe it go forward, vnto the common cauſe, eſpecially to our holie ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, apoſtolike and / romiſh religion, ſith that they who were wont to fight togither for the propagation therof, ſhall through this accident (if it be not remedied) be diſvnited &amp; forced to turne their weapons each againſt other: to eſchew the falling whereinto wee pray you to beleeue, that for our parts we will do whatſoeuer poſsibly we may: of ſuch force is the zeale that we beare vnto our ſaid religion, as hetherto we haue ſufficiently cauſed to appeare. We alſo, ſo much as in vs lieth, exhort and pray you, to procure ſupplications vnto God in your churches for this revnion, as alſo for the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto vs due, to be obſerued according as is meet, and not to ſuffer the inhabitants of our town of <hi>M.</hi> to depart the right pathes therof: but to admoniſh and perſwade them to remaine quiet and conſtant in their loyalties to their king: and in vnion and concord one with an other, ſo to maintaine and preſerue themſelues vnder our obedience, and not to incur the diſcommodities for them prouided, if they take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other courſe. Thus beſides that you ſhal performe an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worthy your diſcretions, fidelities and duties, which may be a notable example to al ſubiects, we ſhal yeeld you thanks for euer, and acknowledge it to you and yours.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Giuen at Chartres.</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>May.</hi> 1588.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The copie of a Letter written by the duke of <hi>Guize</hi> vnto the king, <date>the xvii, day of May.</date>
               </head>
               <p>SIr, ſuch is my miſhap, that they which of long time haue by ſundry ſleights ſought to eſtrange me from your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and fauour, haue beene of power ſufficient to make whatſoeuer the good endeuours that I haue put in practiſe, for to come neere you, and by my ſeruices to grow into your Maieſties liking, vtterly vnprofitable. Wherof of late days (to my great griefe) I haue had more triall then euer before. For
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:28834:33"/>
being wearied with ſo many falſe bruits and ſlanders where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue vſed to keepe your maieſtie in miſtruſt of me, I thought it good, euen with the hazarde of that with which I was threatned, to iuſtifie my life, being (to that end reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) to come vnto you with ſo ſmall companie and ſo great confidence &amp; franchiſe, as I hoped therby to ſhew, and that to euery man, that I was farre off from that wherewith my euil willers ſo ſubtilly ſought to bring me into ſuſpition: but the enimies of the common peace and mine, not being able to abide my preſence about you, as imagining that the ſame would in fewe dayes diſcouer the ſubtilties which they practiſed to bring mee into hatred, and fearing leaſt by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little I ſhould recouer your fauour, they choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their pernitious counſailes to bring againe al things into confuſion, and to bring both your ſtate and your towne of <hi>Paris</hi> into hazarde, then to ſuffer mee to be about you. Their bad minds haue manifeſtly beene deſcried in the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which without the Queene your mothers knowledge, and the aduiſe of your wiſeſt Counſailors, they haue cauſed your maieſtie to take: that is, by an vnuſuall way, and in time full of ſuſpition and partialitie, to bring in forces into your towne of <hi>Paris,</hi> and to ſeiſe vpon the publike places there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: yea, the common ſpeech is, that they hoped, hauing once become maſters thereof, to be able to induce you to manie things farre from your nature, which alſo I had rather paſſe ouer in ſilence. The terrour heereof, ſir, hath forced your good and faithfull ſubiectes to arme themſelues, through a iuſt feare, leaſt by this meanes the thinges whereof long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were threatned might bee put in execution. But God of his holie grace contained matters in better ſtaie then man coulde hope, and as it were miraculouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued your towne out of a moſt perillous hazarde. The beginning, courſe and euent of this matter hath ſo iuſtified my intents, that I ſuppoſe your Maieſtie and all the worlde doth thereby cleerely perceiue howe farre my behauiours haue differed from thoſe practiſes, whereof my ſlanderers doo ſeeke to make mee guiltie. The manner howe I did voluntarilie habandon my ſelfe into your power, do ſhewe what confidence I repoſed in your goodneſſe, and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:28834:33"/>
of my conſcience. The ſtate wherin I was found when I firſt vnderſtood of this enterpriſe (which many of your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants can teſtifie) doo ſufficiently ſhewe that I ſtoode in no doubt of being hurt, neither had any mind to enterpriſe, as remaining more ſolitarie and vnarmed in my houſe, then one of my calling either may or ought to doo. The reſpect that I haue vſed, containing my ſelfe within the ſimple bounds of a iuſt defence, may ſufficiently teſtifie vnto you, that no occaſion whatſoeuer, is able to make me fal from the duetie of a moſt humble ſubiect. The paines that I tooke to reſtraine the people, and keepe them from proceeding to thoſe effectes which ſuch accidents doo for the moſt part bring in, do diſcharge me from the ſlanders heretofore laid vppon mee. viz. <hi>That I was want to trouble your towne of Paris,</hi> My care to preſerue euen thoſe whome I knowe to haue plaied ſome badde partes againſt mee about you, by the prouocation of my enimies, doo manifeſtly declare to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man that I neuer intended to attempt anie thing againſt your ſeruants and officers, as they haue falſely accuſed mee. My behauiours toward your Suitzers, their captaines, and the ſouldiers of your guard doo ſufficientlie aſſure you, that I neuer feared any thing ſo much, as to diſpleaſe you. If your maieſtie haue knowne of all theſe particularities (as I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that ſundrie your good ſeruants, louers of publike quietneſſe, who are witneſſes of the ſame, haue not concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them from you) I doo aſſuredly thinke that you are thereby perſwaded that I neuer had, euen the leaſt of thoſe badde meanings whereof my enimies through falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes haue ſought to bring mee into hatred: and I hope ſir, that the ende wil yeeld more aſſured teſtimonie thereof, as hauing conceiued one of the greateſt griefes that coulde happen mee, when I heard that your maieſty was reſolued to depart: becauſe your ſo ſuddeine going away tooke from me al meanes of being able, according to my purpoſe, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate euerie thing to your contentation: whereto I did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redy ſee them diſpoſed at ſuch time as it pleaſed the Q. your mother to come hither, wherof I gaue her ſuch teſtimonies as I account ſhe cannot but thinke to be certaine. Howbeit ſith I then could not, yet will I ſir ſtill continue the ſame minde,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:28834:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and hope ſo to beare my ſelfe, that your maieſtie ſhall iudge me to be a moſt faithfull ſubiect and ſeruant, who deſireth nothing ſo much, as by wel doing and procuring the benefit of your realme to obtaine the good happe of your fauour, which I will neuer ceaſe ſeeking vntill God hath giuen mee the meanes: whome I beſeech, ſir, to grant vnto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From Paris</hi> 
                     <date>the 17. <hi>of May.</hi> 1588.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An extract out of other letters written by the ſaid L. duke of <hi>Guize.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE had enough to do to ſtrengthen our ſelues againſt the ſleights daily framed againſt vs, wherby to ſeeke ſome colour not to paſſe into <hi>Guyenne</hi> againſt the heretikes: we went to ſatiſfie the king about his garriſons in <hi>Picardie,</hi> and albeit this regiment had not taken the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe, but to refreſh ancient enmities, and to ſeeke newe contritions, yet did we force our friends for one moneth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably to ſuffer the forces of <hi>Eſpernon</hi> ouer their heades, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afreſh for the greater hinderance, the ſaid <hi>Eſpernon</hi> went to ſeeke ſome brawle in <hi>Normandie,</hi> and there had he found it verie hot, had not we, vpon a deſire to ſee the war againſt the heretikes proceede, husbanded his affaires and procured our friends to refraine, and not to hinder, or in any wiſe to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt him. All this notwithſtanding, the more to entangle vs as wel through theſe ſuperfluous garriſons and loſt iournies, as alſo for the vtter breaking of the courſe of this warre, and turning it againſt vs, they framed vs a match to our honor, ſpreading abroade diuers rumors, whereby to cauſe vs to be more feared then the heretikes themſelues: as that wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in a maſſacre at <hi>Paris: That we purpoſed to ſeiſe vpon the kings perſon: That we meant to ſacke the towne, and ſo to leauie coine wherewith to make warre againſt whom we liſt,</hi> with manie other like impreſsions which they beate into his maieſties heade with the beſt colours that they coulde, ſo to make them the more receiueable. This was their laſt ſleight, which alſo driue vs into greateſt diſpaire, conſidering that the king went
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:28834:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
about rather to prouide for theſe miſtruſtes then to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the warre againſt the heretikes: alſo that our wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was ſuch, as among ſome to be ſo accounted of, yea ſo farre foorth, as euen his holines thereupon tooke an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by a writing of his, to exhort vs to fidelitie toward the king our ſoueraine. This diſpaire, I ſay, at the laſt impreſsion thereof tooke ſure hold of men, when I vnderſtood that his maieſtie ſtrengthened his guarde with foure enſignes of Frenchmen, and three of Zwitzers, ſo that to the end not to remaine ſo much as one houre in ſuſpition of ſo villanous actions, I came about twelue of the clock into <hi>Paris,</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with eight gentlemen, and through the middeſt of al the guards aforeſaid, I paſſed to kiſſe his maieſties hands, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with me no other ſafe conduct then my ſeruices, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the confidence that euery good ſubiect ought to repoſe in his king. This franchiſe, ſinceritie and open heart, ſhould, as I thought, haue brought me a cleare iuſtification from all theſe paſſed falſe reports. And in truth there was no honeſt man but was glad in his minde, as euery one might manifeſtly perceaue. The next day, being ſtill in my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence aſſured, I was all the day about the king, ſometime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed in the <hi>Tuilleries,</hi> diſcourſing of the voyage into <hi>Guien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> &amp; of this war, whereto I was ſo affectionate. In theſe days, as it is to be preſumed, the king tooke informations from all parts, whither I had any greater traine than the ſame that was ſeene at my comming: Then knowing, as the truth was, that I was thus alone, and had not ſo much as one man of warre within forty leagues of me, ſee, the very next morning the twelfth of May, there entred by day twelue enſignes of Zwitzers and eight enſignes of French footmen at <hi>S. Honors</hi> gate, beſides the foure of the guard, the king &amp; all his court being on horſebacke to receiue them. The maſter of the campe of the regiment of the guards, and the Zwitzers Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels were commanded to go &amp; ſeiſe vpon al the ſtrengthes of <hi>Paris,</hi> and leaſt they ſhould finde any let, the inhabitantes were from the one end of the towne diſtributed cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to their quarters, ſo to breed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a deſire to breake off themſelues through the care of abandoning their wiues &amp; children in ſuch an accident. While theſe thinges were thus
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:28834:35"/>
ordered, I being a ſleepe in my lodging with ſo ſmall a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie (for my traine, was not yet come from <hi>Soiſſons</hi>) as God would, while they were diſtributing their forces into ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie places, I had leaſure to be aduertiſed thereof, and ſundry Gentlemen my friends, being at <hi>Paris</hi> about their affaires, came vnto me: but eſpecially God myraculouſly ſtirred vp all the people with one conſent to runne to armes, and without any conference together, being aſſured of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and through ſome order which ſuddenlie I tooke among them, of themſelues they went about to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate their affaires, &amp; on euery ſide to fortifie themſelues within tenne paces of the forreine power, and that with ſuch readines and vehemencie, that in leſſe than two houres they warned the ſaid troopes preſently to retire out of the towne and ſuburbes. Hereupon alſo about the ſame time it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in ſome quarter a Switzer to wound a townſman, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the towneſmen fell vpon the Switzers that were there, of whome they ſlew ſome twelue or fifteene, wounded ſome twentie or fiue and twentie, and vnarmed the reſt. In an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place ſome companies of the kinges guardes were alſo vnarmed &amp; caſt into the houſes, where with their Captaines they were forced to ſhut vp themſelues. Here uppon I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched through the towne, and at my firſt comming, deliuered nine hundred Switzers priſoners, and ſundry of the ſouldiers of the guard, whome I cauſed to be ſafely conueyed to the <hi>Louure.</hi> This day (all thinges ſhining with the infallible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of God) being come to an end, I went through al the ſtreetes vntill two houres after midnight, praying, entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and threatning the people, ſo that through Gods grace there enſued neither murther, maſſacre, pilferie, or loſſe of one pennie, or of any one droppe of bloud ouer and aboue the aforeſaid, albeit the people were extreemely enuenimed, as knowing (ſaid they) that there were twentie gibets rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die together with ſundrie ſchaffalds, and that they had ſeene the executioners of high Iuſtice ready to put to death a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or ſixe ſcore perſons, whom they named, and I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you ſhould imagine then I write downe. I can not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the great contentation that this woonderfull grace of God bredde in mee. Firſt, for that I ſee my hand ſo clearely
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:28834:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
freed from theſe ſuſpitions of ſacke and maſſacre which they had endeuored to perſwade ſo manie good men of: for ſith I was able to performe it and yet ſo happely kept it from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowne, I thereby ſtopped all my enimies mouthes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe I gaue ſufficient proofe of my zeale to my kings ſeruice, and how in that I procured the deliuerie euen of the weapons which had beene borne againſt my ſelfe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with their fifes and droms, the reconducting of the priſoners, the returning of their enſignes, and the deliuerie of the beſieged, &amp; ſo declined in no iot from the due reſpect in matter where the moſt conſtant might haue loſt it. Then laboured they ſo much that they perſwaded the king to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, foure and twentie houres after that I might (if I had liſt) haue ſtaied him, but God forbid that I ſhould ſo much as haue dreamed thereof. Since his departure his Maieſtie hath had ſome other counſaile and bitterneſſe. I tooke into my handes the <hi>Arſenall,</hi> the <hi>Baſtile</hi> and other the ſtrong pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and procured the coffers of his excheker to be ſealed vp, to the end to conſigne the whole into his Maieſties handes when he ſhall be at peace, as wee hope to yeeld him through our prayers to God, and the interceſsion of his holineſſe and all Chriſtian Princes, and in reſpect of this notable and not common proofe of fidelitie which it hath pleaſed him to commit into my handes. Otherwiſe, if this miſchiefe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, I hope by the ſame meanes to preſerue both the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Catholikes, and to ſet them free from the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution which the heretikes confederates that are about the king did prepare for them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
